<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Misc | Matt Aimonetti]]></title>
  <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/articles/categories/misc/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/"/>
  <updated>2012-04-26T10:48:23+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matt Aimonetti]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning from Rails' failures]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2012/02/29/learning-from-rails-failures/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-29T07:48:08+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2012/02/29/learning-from-rails-failures</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ruby on Rails undisputedly changed the way web frameworks are designed. Rails became a reference when it comes to leveraging conventions, easy baked in feature set and a rich ecosystem. However, I think that Rails did and still does a lot of things pretty poorly.  By writing this post, I'm not trying to denigrate Rails, there are many other people out there already doing that. My hope is that by listing what I think didn't and still doesn't go well, we can learn from our mistakes and improve existing solutions or create better new ones.</p>

<p><a href="http://merbist.com/2012/02/29/learning-from-rails-failures/train_fail/"><img src="http://merbist.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/02/train_fail-300x188.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2>Migration/upgrades</h2>

<p>Migrating a Rails App from a version to the other is very much like playing the lottery, you are almost sure you will lose. To be more correct, you know things will break, you just don't know what, when and how. The Rails team seems to think that everybody is always running on the cutting edge version and don't consider people who prefer to stay a few version behind for stability reasons. What's worse is that plugins/gems might or might not compatible with the version you are updating to, but you will only know that by trying yourself and letting others try and report potential issues.</p>

<p>This is for me, by far, the biggest issue with Rails and something that should have been fixed a long time ago. If you're using the WordPress blog engine, you know how easy and safe it is to upgrade the engine or the plugins. Granted WordPress isn't a web dev framework, but it gives you an idea of what kind of experience we should be striving for.</p>

<p> </p>

<h2>Stability vs playground zone</h2>

<p>New features are cool and they help make the platform more appealing to new comers. They also help shape the future of a framework. But from my perspective, that shouldn't come to the cost of stability. Rails 3's new asset pipeline is a good example of a half-baked solution shoved in a release at the last minute and creating a nightmare for a lot of us trying to upgrade. I know, I know, you can turn off the asset pipeline and it got better since it was first released. But shouldn't that be the other way around? Shouldn't fun new ideas risking the stability of an app or making migration harder, be off by default and turned on only by people wanting to experiment? When your framework is young, it's normal that you move fast and sometimes break, but once it matures, these things shouldn't happen.</p>

<p> </p>

<h2>Public/private/plugin APIs</h2>

<p>This is more of a recommendation than anything else. When you write a framework in a very dynamic language like Ruby, people will "monkey patch" your code to inject features. Sometimes it is due to software design challenges, sometimes it's because people don't know better. However,  by not explicitly specifying what APIs are private (they can change at anytime, don't touch), what APIs are public (stable, will be slowly deprecated when they need to be changed) and which ones are for plugin devs only (APIs meant for instrumentation, extension etc..), you are making migration to newer versions much harder. You see, if you have a small, clean public API, then it's easy to see what could break, warn developers and avoid migration nightmares. However, you need to start doing that early on in your project, otherwise you will end up like Rails where all code can potentially change anytime.</p>

<p> </p>

<h2>Rails/Merb merge was a mistake</h2>

<p>This is my personal opinion and well, feel free to disagree, nobody will ever be able to know to for sure. Without explaining what happened behind closed doors and the various personal motivations, looking at the end result, I agree with the group of people thinking that the merge didn't turn up to be a good thing. For me, Rails 3 isn't significantly better than Rails 2 and it took forever to be released. You still can't really run a mini Rails stack like promised. I did hear that Strobe (company who was hiring Carl Lerche, Yehuda Katz and contracted Jose Valim) used to have an ActionPack based, mini stack but it was never released and apparently only Rails core members really knew what was going on there. Performance in vanilla Rails 3 are only now getting close to what you had with Rails 2 (and therefore far from the perf you were getting with Merb). Thread-safety is still OFF by default meaning that by default your app uses a giant lock only allowing a process to handle 1 request at a time. For me, the flexibility and performance focus of Merb were mainly lost in the merge with Rails. (Granted, some important things such as ActiveModel, cleaner internals and others have made their way into Rails 3)</p>

<p>But what's worse than everything listed so far is that the lack of competition and the internal rewrites made Rails lose its headstart.  Rails is very much HTML/view focused, its primarily strength is to make server side views trivial and it does an amazing job at that. But let's be honest, that's not the future for web dev. The future is more and more logic pushed to run on the client side (in JS) and the server side being used as an API serving data for the view layer. I'm sorry but adding support for CoffeeScript doesn't really do much to making Rails evolve ahead of what it currently is. Don't get me wrong, I'm a big fan of CoffeeScript, that said I still find that Rails is far from being optimized to developer web APIs in Rails. You can certainly do it, but you are basically using a tool that wasn't designed to write APIs and you pay the overhead for that. If there is one thing I wish Rails will get better at is to make writing pure web APIs better (thankfully there is Sinatra). But at the end of the day, I think that two projects with different philosophies and different approaches are really hard to merge, especially in the open source world. I wouldn't go as far as saying like others that Rails lost its sexiness to node.js because of the wasted time, but I do think that things would have been better for all if that didn't happen. However, I also have to admit that I'm not sure how much of a big deal that is. I prefer to leave the past behind, learn from my own mistake and move on.</p>

<p> </p>

<h2>Technical debts</h2>

<p>Here I'd like to stop to give a huge props to Aaron "<a href="http://twitter.com/tenderlove">@tenderlove</a>" Patterson, the man who's actively working to reduce the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technical_debt">technical debts</a> in the Rails code base. This is a really hard job and definitely not a very glamorous one. He's been working on various parts of Rails including its router and its ORM (ActiveRecord). Technical debts are unfortunately normal in most project, but sometimes they are overwhelming to the point that nobody dares touching the code base to clean it up. This is a hard problem, especially when projects move fast like Rails did. But looking back, I think that you want to start tackling technical debts on the side as you move on so you avoid getting to the point that you need a hero to come up and clean the piled errors made in the past. But don't pause your entire project to clean things up otherwise you will lose market, momentum and excitement. I feel that this is also very much true for any legacy project you might pick up as a developer.</p>

<p> </p>

<h2>Keep the cost of entry level low</h2>

<p>Getting started with Rails used to be easier. This can obviously argued since it's very subjective, but from my perspective I think we forgot where we come from and we involuntary expect new comers to come with unrealistic knowledge. Sure, Rails does much more than it used to do, but it's also much harder to get started. I'm not going to argue how harder  it is now or why we got there. Let's just keep in mind that it is a critical thing that should always be re-evaluated. Sure, it's harder when you have an open source project, but it's also up to the leadership to show that they care and to encourage and mentor volunteers to  focus on this important part of a project.</p>

<p> </p>

<h2>Documentation</h2>

<p>Rails documentation isn't bad, but it's far from being great. Documentation certainly isn't one of the Ruby's community strength, especially compared with the Python community, but what saddens me is to see the state of <a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/">the official documentation</a> which, should, in theory be the reference. Note that the Rails guides are usually well written and provide value, but they too often seem too light and not useful when you try to do something not totally basic (for instance use an ActiveModel compliant object). That's probably why most people don't refer to them or don't spend too much time there. I'm not trying to blame anyone there. I think that the people who contributed theses guides did an amazing job, but if you want to build a strong and easy to access community, great documentation is key. Look at the <a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.3/">Django</a> documentation as a good example. That said, I also need to acknowledge the amazing job done by many community members such as <a href="http://railscasts.com/">Ryan Bates</a> and <a href="http://ruby.railstutorial.org/">Michael Hartl</a> consistently providing high value external documentation via the <a href="http://railscasts.com/">railscasts</a> and the intro to <a href="http://ruby.railstutorial.org/">Rails tutorial</a> available for free.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>In conclusion, I think that there is a lot to learn from Rails, lots of great things as well as lots of things you would want to avoid. We can certainly argue on Hacker News or via comments about whether or not I'm right about Rails failures, my point will still be that the mentioned issues should be avoided in any projects, Rails here is just an example. Many of these issues are currently being addressed by the Rails team but wouldn't it be great if new projects learn from older ones and avoid making the same mistakes? So what other mistakes do you think I forgot to mention and that one should be very careful of avoiding?</p>

<p> </p>

<h3>Updates:</h3>

<ol>
<li><p>Rails 4 had an API centric app generator but it <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/commit/6db930cb5bbff9ad824590b5844e04768de240b1">was quickly reverted</a> and will live as gem until it's mature enough.</p></li>
<li><p>Rails 4 improved the ActiveModel API to be simpler to get started with. See <a href="http://blog.plataformatec.com.br/2012/03/barebone-models-to-use-with-actionpack-in-rails-4-0/">this blog</a> post for more info.</p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Books to read in 2012 - recommended to me by Twitter]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2011/12/30/books-to-read-in-2012-recommended-to-me-by-twitter/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-30T15:28:13+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2011/12/30/books-to-read-in-2012-recommended-to-me-by-twitter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today, I asked on Twitter what non-technical books I should read in 2012.</p>

<p>I was nicely surprised to see so many of my followers send recommendations. Here is a list of 25 books that like-minded people suggested I read. Hopefully you will find a book or two to read too. Feel free to send more recommendations via the comments.</p>

<p> </p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0307593312/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0307593312"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=0307593312&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0307593312" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0307593312/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0307593312">1Q84 by Haruki Murakami</a></p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/mrb_bk">@mrb_bk</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/chadfowler">@chadfowler</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0385240899/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0385240899"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=0385240899&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0385240899" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0385240899/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0385240899">The Floating Opera and The End of the Road by John Barth</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0385240899" alt="" /></p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/chadfowler">@chadfowler</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0613663616/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0613663616"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=0613663616&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0613663616" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0613663616/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0613663616">Into Thin Air by Jon Krakauer</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0613663616" alt="" /></p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/bradly">@bradly</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0375714367/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0375714367"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=0375714367&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0375714367" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0375714367/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0375714367">Cutting for Stone by Abraham Verghese</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0375714367" alt="" /></p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/bradly">@bradly</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0452011876/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0452011876"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=0452011876&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0452011876" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0452011876/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0452011876">Atlas Shrugged by Ayn Rand</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0452011876" alt="" /></p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/bradly">@bradly</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0307474720/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0307474720"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=0307474720&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0307474720" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0307474720/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0307474720">Cien años de soledad by Gabriel Garcia Marquez</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0307474720" alt="" /> (es)</p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/romanandreg">@romanandreg</a> &amp; <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/jrfernandez">@jrfernandez</a> &amp; <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/edgarschmidt">@edgarschmidt</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0060883286/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0060883286"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=0060883286&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0060883286" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0060883286/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0060883286">One Hundred Years of Solitude by Gabriel García Marquez</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0060883286" alt="" /></p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/romanandreg">@romanandreg</a> &amp; <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/jrfernandez">@jrfernandez</a> &amp; <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/edgarschmidt">@edgarschmidt</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0553348981/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0553348981"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=0553348981&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0553348981" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0553348981/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0553348981">Jitterbug Perfume by Tom Robbins</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0553348981" alt="" /></p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/supaspoida">@supaspoida</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0062041266/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0062041266"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=0062041266&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0062041266" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0062041266/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0062041266">The Sisters Brothers by Patrick deWitt</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0062041266" alt="" /></p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/dennismajor1">@dennismajor1</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0312278497/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0312278497"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=0312278497&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0312278497" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0312278497/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0312278497">The Glass Bead Game by Hermann Hesse</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0312278497" alt="" /></p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/dj2sincl">@dj2sincl</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0679775439/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0679775439"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=0679775439&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0679775439" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0679775439/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0679775439">The Wind-Up Bird Chronicle by Haruki Murakami</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0679775439" alt="" /></p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/chadfowler">@chadfowler</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0983873100/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0983873100"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=0983873100&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0983873100" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0983873100/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0983873100">Mindfire by Scott Berkun</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0983873100" alt="" /></p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/lucasdicioccio">@lucasdicioccio</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/2226052577/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=2226052577"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=2226052577&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=2226052577" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/2226052577/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=2226052577">Les Fourmis by Bernard Werber</a> (fr)</p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/twitty_tim">@twitty_tim</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0375725849/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0375725849"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=0375725849&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0375725849" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0375725849/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0375725849">Perfume: The Story of a Murderer by Patrick Suskind</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0375725849" alt="" /></p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/twitty_tim">@twitty_tim</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1613820259/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=1613820259"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=1613820259&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=1613820259" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1613820259/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=1613820259">Les Miserables by Victor Hugo</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=1613820259" alt="" /> (en, free ebook)</p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/tutec">@tutec</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0307292134/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0307292134"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=0307292134&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0307292134" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0307292134/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0307292134">Song Of Ice and Fire by George R.R. Martin</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0307292134" alt="" /> (Game of Thrones saga)</p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/eeppa">@eeppa</a> &amp; <a href="http://twitter.com/jarin">@jarin</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0765329468/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0765329468"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=0765329468&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0765329468" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0765329468/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0765329468">Clockwork Century by Cherie Priest</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0765329468" alt="" /></p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/eeppa">@eeppa</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1590201183/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=1590201183"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=1590201183&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=1590201183" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1590201183/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=1590201183">The Darkness that Comes Before by R. Scott Bakker</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=1590201183" alt="" /></p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/eeppa">@eeppa</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B003GAN3VE/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B003GAN3VE"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=B003GAN3VE&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B003GAN3VE" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B003GAN3VE/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B003GAN3VE">Drood by Dan Simmons</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B003GAN3VE" alt="" /></p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/eeppa">@eeppa</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0316068225/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0316068225"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=0316068225&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0316068225" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0316068225/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0316068225">This Is Water by David Foster Wallace</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0316068225" alt="" /></p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/atduskgreg">@atduskgreg</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B005DI71QA/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B005DI71QA"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=B005DI71QA&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B005DI71QA" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B005DI71QA/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B005DI71QA">Anathem by Neal Stephenson</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B005DI71QA" alt="" /></p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/jarin">@jarin</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0812550706/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0812550706"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=0812550706&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0812550706" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0812550706/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0812550706">Ender's Game by Orson Scott Card</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0812550706" alt="" /> (entire saga)</p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/jarin">@jarin</a> &amp; <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/edgarschmidt">@edgarschmidt</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/344245302X/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=344245302X"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=344245302X&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=344245302X" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/344245302X/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=344245302X">Snow Crash by Neal Stephenson</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=344245302X" alt="" /></p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/jarin">@jarin</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1422171647/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=1422171647"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=1422171647&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=1422171647" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1422171647/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=1422171647">Fixing the Game by Roger L. Martin</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=1422171647" alt="" /></p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/jarkko">@jarkko</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0307387895/ref=as_li_ss_il?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0307387895"><img src="http://ws.assoc-amazon.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ASIN=0307387895&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822" alt="" /></a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0307387895" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0307387895/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0307387895">The Road by Cormac McCarthy</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=merbist-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0307387895" alt="" /></p>

<p>suggested by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/mrreynolds">@mrreynolds</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Developing a Curriculum]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2011/12/21/developing-a-curriculum/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-21T06:57:27+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2011/12/21/developing-a-curriculum</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I asked a friend of mine to give me pointers on how to develop a curriculum (he used to teach an education PHD program), after discussing his response on Twitter, people asked me to put it somewhere, so here it is:</p>

<p>Process to develop a curriculum:</p>

<p><strong>Purpose</strong>. <em>Know why you're doing what you're doing.</em></p>

<ul>
<li>You know how to do this.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Product</strong>. <em>Start with the end in mind.</em></p>

<ul>
<li><p>What does the student look like when they walk out the door at the end of the training.</p></li>
<li><p>Usually, we break these down into <strong>Knowledge</strong>, <strong>Skills</strong>, or <strong>Attitudes</strong>.</p></li>
<li><p>Sometimes it's helpful to see a photograph or drawing of a someone who finished the program and just talk about what they can do that makes them successful.</p></li>
<li><p>This "product" should be connected and help you accomplish your mission</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Practices</strong>. <em>Then ask yourself, "How do people become like this?"</em></p>

<ul>
<li><p>If you can break down your Product into 3-5 bit-sized chunks, then see how people learn each one of those skills, gain each one of those knowledge points, and how to they gain the attitudes you want them to have.</p></li>
<li><p>This one is much easier the more experience you have in seeing people develop the "Product."</p></li>
<li><p>This is also easier to determine when you understand <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Learning_theory_(education">Learning Theory</a>).</p></li>
<li><p>The results from this section will result in a list of:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>       Activities or experiences</p></li>
<li><p>       Resources. What books, website, teachers, software, etc. will help them learn more effectively and efficiently</p></li>
<li><p>       Assessments. How you would know if the activity was helpful?</p></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Plans</strong>. <em>Make your plans based on the practices you've determined you've needed.</em></p>

<p> </p>

<p>On a related topic, Chad Fowler posted an interesting <a href="http://chadfowler.com/2011/12/21/re-thinking-software-development-education">blog post about what LivingSocial is doing to change the software development education</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Data safety and GIL removal]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2011/10/18/data-safety-and-gil-removal/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-18T15:19:17+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2011/10/18/data-safety-and-gil-removal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After my recent <a href="http://rubyconf11.merbist.com">RubyConf talk</a> and <a href="http://merbist.com/2011/10/03/about-concurrency-and-the-gil/">follow up post addressing the Ruby &amp; Python's Global Interpreter Lock</a> (aka GVL/Global VM Lock). a lot of people asked me to explain what I meant by "data safety". While my point isn't to defend one approach or the other, I spent a lot of time explaining why C Ruby and C Python use a GIL and where it matters and where it matters less. As a reminder and as mentioned by Matz himself, the main reason why C Ruby still has a GIL is data safety. But if this point isn't clear to you, you might be missing the main argument supporting the use of a GIL.</p>

<p>Showing obvious concrete examples of data corruption due to unsafe threaded code isn't actually as easy at it sounds. First of all, even with a GIL, developers can write unsafe threaded code. So we need to focus only on the safety problems raised by removing the GIL. To demonstrate what I mean, I will try to create some race conditions and show you the unexpected results you might get. Again, before you go crazy on the comments, remember that threaded code is indeterministic and the code below might potentially work on your machine and that's exactly why it is hard to demonstrate. Race conditions depend on many things, but in this case I will focus on race conditions affecting basic data structures since it might be the most surprising.</p>

<h2>Example:</h2>

<p><code>ruby
@array, threads = [], []
4.times do
  threads &lt;&lt; Thread.new { (1..100_000).each {|n| @array &lt;&lt; n} }
end
threads.each{|t| t.join }
puts @array.size
</code></p>

<p>In the above example, I'm creating an instance variable of Array type and I start 4 threads. Each of these threads adds 100,000 items to the array. We then wait for all the threads to be done and check the size of the array.</p>

<p>If you run this code in C Ruby the end result will be as expected:</p>

<pre><code>400000
</code></pre>

<p>Now if you switch to JRuby you might be surprised by the output. If you are lucky you will see the following:</p>

<pre><code>ConcurrencyError: Detected invalid array contents due to unsynchronized modifications with concurrent users
        &lt;&lt; at org/jruby/RubyArray.java:1147
  __file__ at demo.rb:3
      each at org/jruby/RubyRange.java:407
  __file__ at demo.rb:3
      call at org/jruby/RubyProc.java:274
      call at org/jruby/RubyProc.java:233
</code></pre>

<p>This is actually a good thing. JRuby detects that you are unsafely modifying an instance variable across threads and that data corruption will occur. However, the exception doesn't always get raised and you will potentially see results such as:</p>

<pre><code>335467
342397
341080
</code></pre>

<p>This is a sign that the data was corrupted but that JRuby didn't catch the unsynchronized modification. On the other hand MacRuby and Rubinius 2 (dev) won't raise any exceptions and will just corrupt the data, outputting something like:</p>

<pre><code>294278
285755
280704
279865
</code></pre>

<p>In other words, if not manually synchronized, shared data can easily be corrupted. You might have two threads modifying the value of the same variable and one of the two threads will step on top of the other leaving you with a race condition. You only need 2 threads accessing the same instance variable at the same time to get a race condition. My example uses more threads and more mutations to make the problem more obvious. Note that TDD wouldn't catch such an issue and even extensive testing will provide very little guarantee that your code is thread safe.</p>

<p> </p>

<h2>So what? Thread safety isn't a new problem.</h2>

<p>That's absolutely correct, ask any decent Java developer out there, he/she will tell how locks are used to "easily" synchronize objects to make your code thread safe. They might also mention the deadlocks and other issues related to that, but that's a different story. One might also argue that when you write web apps, there is very little shared data and the chances of corrupting data across concurrent requests is very small since most of the data is kept in a shared data store outside of the process.</p>

<p>All these arguments are absolutely valid, the challenge is that you have a large community and a large amount of code out there that expects a certain behavior. And removing the GIL does change this behavior. It might not be a big deal for you because you know how to deal with thread safety, but it might be a big deal for others and C Ruby is by far the most used Ruby implementation. It's basically like saying that automatic cars shouldn't be made and sold, and everybody has to switch to stick shifts. They have better gas mileage, I personally enjoy driving then and they are cheaper to build. Removing the GIL is a bit like that. There is a cost associated with this decision and while this cost isn't insane, the people in charge prefer to not pay it.</p>

<p> </p>

<h2>Screw that, I'll switch to Node.js</h2>

<p>I heard a lot of people telling me they were looking into using Node.js because it has a better design and no GIL. While I like Node.js and if I were to implement a chat room or an app keeping connections for a long time, I would certainly compare it closely to EventMachine, I also think that this argument related to the GIL is absurd. First, you have other Ruby implementations which don't have a GIL and are really stable (i.e: JRuby) but then Node basically works the same as Ruby with a GIL. Yes, Node is evented and single threaded but when you think about it, it behaves the same as Ruby 1.9 with its GIL. Many requests come in and they are handled one after the other and because IO requests are non-blocking, multiple requests can be processed concurrently but not in parallel. Well folks, that's exactly how C Ruby works too, and unlike popular believe, most if not all the popular libraries making IO requests are non blocking (when using 1.9). So, next time you try to justify you wanting to toy with Node, please don't use the GIL argument.</p>

<p> </p>

<h2>What should I do?</h2>

<p>As always, evaluate your needs and see what makes sense for your project. Start by making sure you are using Ruby 1.9 and your code makes good use of threading. Then look at your app and how it behaves, is it CPU-bound or IO-bound. Most web apps out there are IO-bound (waiting for the DB, redis or API calls), and when doing an IO call, Ruby's GIL is released allowing another thread to do its work. In that case, not having a GIL in your Ruby implementation won't help you. However, if your app is CPU-bound, then switching to JRuby or Rubinius might be beneficial. However, don't assume anything until you proved it and remember that making such a change will more than likely require some architectural redesign, especially if using JRuby.  But, hey, it might totally be worth it as many proved it in the past.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>I hope I was able to clarify things a bit further. If you wish to dig further, I would highly recommend you read the many discussions the Python community had in the last few years.</p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[About management]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2011/10/11/about-management/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-11T22:53:40+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2011/10/11/about-management</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I decided to save myself a session to the shrink and instead just write down my reflection on management. Who knows, some of you might help me and/or challenge my thought process.</p>

<p>I recently read a great management book called the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B000UCUX0K/ref=as_li_ss_til?tag=merbist-20&amp;camp=213381&amp;creative=390973&amp;linkCode=as4&amp;creativeASIN=B000UCUX0K&amp;adid=0BP6N5GHZD0EW2N7QVZR&amp;">five dysfunctions of a team by Patrick Lencioni</a> . Instead of telling you what to do, the author highlights behavior patterns that are related to each other and when aggregated result in dysfunctional teams. I really liked the book because instead of a being a cookbook/playbook, this is more a fail book, in other words, it illustrates what you don't want to do and explains why. It highlights very well the relation between various behaviors and nicely illustrates why teams of brilliant people can fail. The <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B000UCUX0K/ref=as_li_ss_til?tag=merbist-20&amp;camp=213381&amp;creative=390973&amp;linkCode=as4&amp;creativeASIN=B000UCUX0K&amp;adid=0BP6N5GHZD0EW2N7QVZR&amp;">Kindle version is at less than $5, go get it</a> and read it on your iPhone/iPad/computer/browser…</p>

<p>So this book somewhat changed my perception of management and leadership. Interesting enough, at Sony, my previous employer, they make a distinction between management and leadership. While they hope managers can be leaders, they don't require them to be and to be honest very few are. I'm not sure that's a good or a bad things, but I, for sure, was under different expectations. Finally, I spent a large amount of my life on the internet working on/with projects where meritocracy, respect and honor were key. The "ranking" is purely based on what your peers think of you and not based on your age/sex/origin/diploma/bank account. I do realize that this model has many pros but also some pretty major cons. My only point is that it did affect my worldview. In my world, seniority, a killer  job title or a fancy suit won't buy you my automatic respect. On the other hand, job well done, great vision, honesty, over achievement will!</p>

<p>Taking these few trains of thoughts in consideration, I started thinking about my own expectations for a good manager/leader. I figured that if I were able to do that, I could possibly be able to define a work environment where I could thrive and maybe one day become a good "manager/leader".</p>

<p>I've always questioned my ability to be a good leader. While most of the time, I have an opinion and can easily decide what I think should be done, I have a hard time relating to people who can't see the "big picture". While I usually can get decent results, I'm aware that it can unfortunately sometime be at the cost of a few bruised egos. I also know I have high expectations for myself and for others and I have a hard time understanding how some people can be ok with the "status-quo". I'm a perfectionist who is only happy when he outperforms his previous achievement. I was raised to challenge and always push myself further, focusing on concrete end-results and achieved goals. And to be honest, that's what I enjoy. But I also know for a fact, that many people are not like that and I can't blame them for looking at things from a different angle and not sharing the same motivations. Furthermore, I know that most people actually don't have the same driven temperament and that's why I've questioned my abilities to lead others.</p>

<p>However, different temperaments can work together as long as there is respect. And by respect, I mean that everyone feel that they were being heard and know that their input was considered and addressed even though the outcome might not be as hoped for. But for respect to happen, you first need trust. And when people trust each other, Lencioni explains that <em>"people don't hold back one with another. They are unafraid to air their dirty laundry. They admit their mistakes, their weaknesses, and their concerns without fear of reprisal"</em>. I think that as simple as it seems, it is the key to a successful team. A good leader should be able to create such an atmosphere where people can trust each other. In fact, I think that if a manger/leader/executive can manage to build trust as defined earlier, his technical skills or lack of vision don't matter as much. He/she will be able to rely on people he trusts to help him make the right decisions. Of course, there is much more than to be a good leader, but I think that with this base, great things can be built, and without it, a much greater effort is required to get some good results.</p>

<p>Based on my findings, I think that I need to work on my communication so others don't feel that they have to hold back and make sure everyone feels that their opinions were considered and addressed. To do that a key element is to admit my mistakes and weaknesses and asking others to help me improve. That's it, sorry for the boring, not technical post. I promise the next one will have at least a code sample.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to - cross domain ajax to a Ruby app]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2011/09/14/how-to-cross-domain-ajax-in-a-ruby-app/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-14T16:11:41+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2011/09/14/how-to-cross-domain-ajax-in-a-ruby-app</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In some cases, you might have a bunch of apps running on different domains/subdomains and/or ports and you would like to make ajax requests between these services. The problem is that browsers wouldn't let you make such requests because of the Same Origin Policy which only allowed them to make request to resources within the same domain.</p>

<p>However, most browsers (IE 8+, Firefox 3.5+, Safari 4+, Chrome) implement a simple way to allow cross domain requests as defined in this <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/cors/">w3C document</a>.</p>

<p>Of course, if your users have an old version of their browser, you  might have to look into jsonp or something else such as cheating by using iframes &amp; setting document.domain. Let's pretend for a minute that 100% of your users are on Chrome. The only thing you need to do is set a response header listing the accepted domains or "*" for all. A simple Rack middleware to do that would look like that.</p>

<p> </p>

<pre><code>class XOriginEnabler
  ORIGIN_HEADER = "Access-Control-Allow-Origin"

  def initialize(app, accepted_domain="*")
    @app = app
    @accepted_domain = accepted_domain
  end

  def call(env)
    status, header, body = @app.call(env)
    header[ORIGIN_HEADER] = @accepted_domain
    [status, header, body]
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>And to use the middleware you would need to set it for use:</p>

<pre><code>use XOriginEnabler
</code></pre>

<p>To enable all requests from whatever origin, or pass the white listed domain(s) as shown below.</p>

<pre><code>use XOriginEnabler, "demo.mysite.com demo.mysite.fr demo.techcrunch.com"
</code></pre>

<p>For a full featured middleware, see <a href="https://github.com/cyu/rack-cors">this project</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ruby optimization example and explanation]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2011/09/05/ruby-optimization-example-and-explaination/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-05T14:58:21+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2011/09/05/ruby-optimization-example-and-explaination</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I wrote a small DSL that allows the user to define some code that then gets executed later on and in different contexts. Imagine something like Sinatra where each route action is defined in a block and then executed in context of an incoming request.</p>

<p>The challenge is that blocks come with their context and you can't execute a block in the context of another one.</p>

<p>Here is a reduction of the challenge I was trying to solve:</p>

<pre><code>class SolutionZero
  def initialize(origin, &amp;block;)
    @origin = origin
    @block = block
  end

  def dispatch
    @block.call
  end
end

SolutionZero.new(42){ @origin + 1 }.dispatch
# undefined method `+' for nil:NilClass (NoMethodError)
</code></pre>

<p>The problem is that the block refers to the @origin instance variable which is not available in its context.
My first workaround was to use instance_eval:</p>

<pre><code>class SolutionOne
  def initialize(origin, &amp;block;)
    @origin = origin
    @block = block
  end

  def dispatch
    self.instance_eval &amp;@block
  end
end

SolutionOne.new(40){ @origin + 2}.dispatch
# 42
</code></pre>

<p>My workaround worked fine, since the block was evaluated in the context of the instance and therefore the @origin ivar is made available to block context. Technically, I was good to go, but I wasn't really pleased with this solution. First using instance_eval often an indication that you are trying to take a shortcut. Then having to convert my block stored as a block back into a proc every single dispatch makes me sad. Finally, I think that this code is probably not performing as well as it could, mainly due to unnecessary object allocations and code evaluation.
I did some benchmarks replacing <a href="https://github.com/ruby/ruby/blob/trunk/vm_eval.c#L1323">instance_eval</a> by <a href="https://github.com/ruby/ruby/blob/trunk/vm_eval.c#L1355">instance_exec</a> since looking at the C code, instance_exec should be slightly faster. Turns out, it is not so I probably missed something when reading the implementation code.</p>

<p>I wrote some more benchmarks and profiled a loop of 2 million dispatches (only the #disptach method call on the same object). The GC profiler report showed that the GC was invoked 287 times and each invocation was blocking the execution for about 0.15ms.
Using Ruby's <a href="http://ruby-doc.org/core/classes/ObjectSpace.html#M001526">ObjectSpace</a> and <a href="http://ruby-doc.org/core/classes/GC.html#M001373">disabling the GC</a> during the benchmark, I could see that each loop allocates an object of type T_NODE which is more than likely our @block ivar converted back into a block. This is quite a waste. Furthermore, having to evaluate our block in a different context every single call surely isn't good for performance.</p>

<p>So instead of doing the work at run time, why not doing it at load time? By that I mean that we can optimize the #dispatch method if we could "precompile" the method body instead of "proxying" the dispatch to an instance_eval call. Here is the code:</p>

<pre><code>class SolutionTwo
  def initialize(origin, &amp;block;)
    @origin = origin
    implementation(block)
  end

  private

  def implementation(block)
    mod = Module.new
    mod.send(:define_method, :dispatch, block)
    self.extend mod
  end
end

SolutionTwo.new(40){ @origin + 2}.dispatch
# 42
</code></pre>

<p>This optimization is based on the fact that the benchmark (and the real life usage) creates the instance once and then calls #dispatch many times. So by making the initialization of our instance a bit slower, we can drastically improve the performance of the method call. We also still need to execute our block in the right context. And finally, each instance might have a different way to dispatch since it is defined dynamically at initialization. To work around all these issues, we create a new module on which we define a new method called dispatch and the body of this method is the passed block. Then we simply our instance using our new module.</p>

<p>Now every time we call #dispatch, a real method is dispatched which is much faster than doing an eval and no objects are allocated. Running the profiler and the benchmarks script used earlier, we can confirm that the GC doesn't run a single time and that the optimized code runs 2X faster!</p>

<p> </p>

<p>Once again, it's yet another example showing that you <a href="http://merbist.com/2010/07/29/object-allocation-why-you-should-care/">should care about object allocation</a> when dealing with code in the critical path. It also shows how to work around the block bindings. Now, it doesn't mean that you have to obsess about object allocation and performance, even if my last implementation is 2X faster than the previous, we are only talking about a few microseconds per dispatch. That said microseconds do add up and creating too many objects will slow down even your faster code since the GC will stop-the-world as its cleaning up your memory. In real life, you probably don't have to worry too much about low level details like that, unless you are working on a framework or sharing your code with others. But at least you can learn and understand why one approach is faster than the other, it might not be useful to you right away, but if you take programming as a craft, it's good to understand how things work under the hood so you can make educated decisions.
 </p>

<h3>Update:</h3>

<p>@apeiros in the comments suggested a solution that works &amp; performs the same as my solution, but is much cleaner:</p>

<pre><code>class SolutionTwo
  def initialize(origin, &amp;block;)
    @origin = origin
    define_singleton_method(:dispatch, block) if block_given?
  end
end
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Go's reflection example]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2011/06/27/golang-reflection-exampl/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-27T12:12:32+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2011/06/27/golang-reflection-exampl</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://golang.org/">Go Programming language</a> is really cool language by Google. According to the sales pitch, it's a <strong><em>"fast, statically typed, compiled language that feels like a dynamically typed, interpreted language"</em></strong>. Well, if you are like me, you don't trust sales pitches because you know that people writing them dont' care about you, they care about their product. However cynical you are, you still have to check the facts. So here is a quick demonstration showing how to use Go's reflection feature.</p>

<p>Installing Go is actually really straight forward on a Mac, and slightly harder on Linux, check <a href="http://golang.org/doc/install.html">this guide </a>to see how to build Go in a few minutes.</p>

<p>Once all setup, you might want to read the documentation to see how to code in Go. Go is actually a kind of nice version of C with a<a href="http://golang.org/doc/go_spec.html"> simplified syntax</a>, no header files, really fast compilation time, a garbage collector and a <a href="http://golang.org/doc/effective_go.html?#interfaces_and_types">simple way to approach object inheritance</a> without turning in the complicated mess C++ is. The language is designed around the concept of <a href="http://golang.org/doc/effective_go.html?h=goroutines#concurrency">goroutines, a very nice way to handle concurrency</a>. It also has some features that Rubyists, Pythonistas and Javascripters wouldn't want to live without such as closures and some they probably wish they had such as <a href="http://golang.org/doc/effective_go.html?#defer">defer</a>. But of the things we are used to with dynamic languages is the concept of reflection. In a nutshell, at runtime, your code can reflect on the type of a given object and let the developer act accordingly. Depending on your programming background that might be obvious or you might not see the value. To be honest, that's not the question here. What I'm interested in showing you is how it works.</p>

<p>For the sake of this demo, let's pretend we want to have a "Dish" data model, each instance of the "Dish" type will have a few attributes, an id, a name, an origin and a custom query which really is a function that we store as an attribute. Here is how we would represent that model in Go:</p>

<pre><code>// Data Model
type Dish struct {
  Id  int
  Name string
  Origin string
  Query func()
}
</code></pre>

<p>This is more or less the equivalent of the following Ruby code:</p>

<pre><code>class Dish
  attr_accessor :id, :name, :origin, :query
end
</code></pre>

<p>Ruby works slightly differently in the sense that defining attribute accessors create getters and setter methods but doesn't technically create instance variables until they are used. Here is what I mean:</p>

<pre><code>shabushabu = Dish.new
shabushabu.instance_variables # =&gt; []
shabushabu.name = "Shabu-Shabu"
shabushabu.instance_variables # =&gt; ["@name"]
shabushabu.origin = "Japan"
shabushabu.instance_variables # =&gt; ["@name", "@origin"]
</code></pre>

<p>Another way of checking on the accessors is to check the methods defined on the object:</p>

<pre><code>shabushabu.methods - Object.new.methods
=&gt; ["name", "name=", "origin", "origin=", "id=", "query", "query="]
</code></pre>

<p>But anyway, this post isn't about Ruby, it's about Go and what we would like is to reflect on an object of "Dish" type and see its attributes. The good news is that the Go language ships with a <a href="http://golang.org/pkg/reflect/">package to do just that</a>. Here is the full implementation:</p>

<pre><code>package main

import(
  "fmt"
  "reflect"
)

func main(){
  // iterate through the attributes of a Data Model instance
  for name, mtype := range attributes(&amp;Dish;{}) {
    fmt.Printf("Name: %s, Type %s\n", name, mtype.Name())
  }
}

// Data Model
type Dish struct {
  Id  int
  Name string
  Origin string
  Query func()
}

// Example of how to use Go's reflection
// Print the attributes of a Data Model
func attributes(m interface{}) (map[string]reflect.Type) {
  typ := reflect.TypeOf(m)
  // if a pointer to a struct is passed, get the type of the dereferenced object
  if typ.Kind() == reflect.Ptr{
    typ = typ.Elem()
  }

  // create an attribute data structure as a map of types keyed by a string.
  attrs := make(map[string]reflect.Type)
  // Only structs are supported so return an empty result if the passed object
  // isn't a struct
  if typ.Kind() != reflect.Struct {
    fmt.Printf("%v type can't have attributes inspected\n", typ.Kind())
    return attrs
  }

  // loop through the struct's fields and set the map
  for i := 0; i &lt; typ.NumField(); i++ {
    p := typ.Field(i)
      if !p.Anonymous {
        attrs[p.Name] = p.Type
      }
     }

  return attrs
}
</code></pre>

<p>Unfortunately, my code highlighter doesn't support the Go syntax, but GitHub does, so here is a <a href="https://gist.github.com/1009629">pretty version</a>.</p>

<p>There are ways of running Go source code like Ruby or Python scripts but in this case, we'll use the compiler &amp; linker provided with Go. I named my source file "example.go", and here is how I compiled, linked and run it:</p>

<pre><code>$ 6g example.go &amp;&amp; 6l example.6 &amp;&amp; ./6.out
Name: Origin, Type string
Name: Id, Type int
Name: Query, Type 
Name: Name, Type string
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see each attribute is printed out with its name and type. The code might seem a bit odd if you never looked at Go before.
Here is a quick rundown of the code:</p>

<p>In our main function, we create a new instance of type Dish on which we call attributes on. The call returns a map on which we iterate through and print the attribute name (key) and type (value).
The attributes function is defined a bit below and and it takes any type of objects (empty interface) and returns a map, which is like a Hash or a Dictionary. The map has keys of String type and values of "Type" type. The "Type" type is defined in the reflect package. Inside the function, 23 then use the previously mentioned reflect package to check on the type and the name of each attribute and assign it to a map object. (note that I'm explicitly returning the map, but I could have done it in a more implicit way)</p>

<p>So there you go, that's how you use reflection in Go. Pretty nifty and simple.</p>

<p> </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sayonara Sony ]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2011/06/10/sayonara-sony/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-10T08:49:30+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2011/06/10/sayonara-sony</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's now official, I have resigned from Sony Computer Entertainment America.</p>

<p><a href="http://merbist.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/playstation-logo.png"><img src="http://merbist.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/playstation-logo-150x150.png" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>I was planning on posting this a bit later but since I was politely escorted out of the building by HR/security, I have more free time to let you know of my decision. Before you ask: No, my decision isn't directly related to the recent PSN/Sony security breach events and no, I don't have your credit card number. More seriously, my decision boils down to something much simpler &amp; concrete: drive and passion.</p>

<p>The concept of drive is very well explained <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u6XAPnuFjJc">in this talk</a> by <a href="http://www.danpink.com/">Dan Pink</a> and illustrated by <a href="http://www.thersa.org/">RSA</a>:</p>

<p>As explained, it is proven that when doing cognitive tasks, there are 3 factors that lead to better performance &amp; personal satisfaction:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Autonomy: engagement vs compliance</p></li>
<li><p>Mastery: get better at stuff</p></li>
<li><p>Purpose: be disruptive but make the world a better place</p></li>
</ul>


<p> </p>

<p>The challenge is that when you work for a big corporation, you rarely see these factors applied. The amount of red tape, management overhead, lack of recognition and accountability result in a low drive by most employees. I think it was the first time in my entire career that I was told by a <a href="http://nateware.com">manager</a> to care less about the quality and end result of our products.</p>

<p>The second important concept that I think is critical when looking at your career is passion. This topic is very well covered in <a href="http://chadfowler.com/">Chad Fowler</a>'s book: <a href="http://pragprog.com/titles/cfcar2/the-passionate-programmer">The Passionate Programmer</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://pragprog.com/titles/cfcar2/the-passionate-programmer"><img src="http://imagery.pragprog.com/products/137/cfcar2_xlargecover.jpg?1298589825" alt="" /></a>Here is a quote from Chad's book:</p>

<blockquote><p>Fulfillment and happiness don’t (often) come by chance. They require thought, intention, action, and a willingness to change course when you’ve made mistakes. [...] It might be a technology or business domain that gets you excited. Or, on the other hand, it might be a specific technology or business domain that drags you down. Or a type of organization. Maybe you’re meant for small teams or big teams. Or rigid processes. Or agile processes. Whatever the mix, take some time to find yours. You can fake it for a while, but a lack of passion will catch up with you and your work.</p></blockquote>

<p> </p>

<p>It's hard to summarize Chad's book into just a few sentences, but what I got from his book is that if, for whatever reason, you lose your passion for your job, you should move on to another place where you can be passionate and excel. In my case, I'm still very much passionate about video game development but I find my passion seriously affected by an unhealthy work environment, bad communication and a lack of desire to change things in concrete ways. As the saying goes, <a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=people+don't+leave+jobs">"People don't leave jobs..."</a></p>

<p> </p>

<h3>What's next for me?</h3>

<p>If you are in the software industry you know that everybody is hiring and that there is a real shortage of talent out there. You probably also receive half a dozen emails per week from recruiters offering you "the best job ever" with an obscene salary. Well, I receive them too. But in this market, you and I can allow ourselves to be picky and to choose the right job for ourselves. By choosing the right job, we are going to be more passionate, more driven, more efficient and bring a lot more value to our employers, who, in return, will hopefully do everything they can to make sure we grow within the company with a strong desire to do even better. As I was considering what I would want to do if I were to leave Sony, I came up with a few ideas about a job:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>I don't want to live to work, but rather, work to live. (kind of an European cliché sentence)</p></li>
<li><p>It's not about the job title.</p></li>
<li><p>It's not about the pay check.</p></li>
<li><p>It's not about how glamourous an industry  is.</p></li>
<li><p>What matters is :</p>

<ul>
<li><p>the company culture.</p></li>
<li><p>the passion coming from the leaders.</p></li>
<li><p>the company's ambitions.</p></li>
<li><p>how the company rewards and respects its employees.</p></li>
<li><p>the autonomy/trust given to the employees.</p></li>
<li><p>the purpose of the company and its potential to disrupt a market/change the world.</p></li>
<li><p>personal growth within the company.</p></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p> </p>

<p>Writing this list helped me realize that I was definitely not in the right place and helped me create a list of criteria to define what kind of job I should be doing instead. As I was thinking about all that, I was reminded of this quote:</p>

<blockquote><p>"One should not pursue goals that are easily achieved. One must develop an instinct for what one can just barely achieve through one's greatest efforts." —Albert Einstein</p></blockquote>

<p>This is probably a personality trait, but I like/need to be at the edge of my confort zone. I need to learn new things, experience new challenges. I need to try to solve unsolved problems. So part of me needs a company with a rich culture, a great a vision and leadership, but another part also needs to be allowed to think creatively, to push the existing boundaries, to challenge myself and to try to achieve things through my greatest efforts.</p>

<p>The challenge is that over the last 5-7 years I have become a Ruby specialist. I have learned to understand and master the language, learning its pros/cons and what goes on "under the hood". I have built small and huge solutions for various domain spaces on top of Ruby. I have shared my knowledge giving talks, books, blog posts. I have also spent a lot of time expanding my own computer science knowledge, looking into other programming languages, frameworks, designs. My job at Sony was interesting due to the fact that Ruby is used in a quite singular way with very specific problems and a lot of C/C++ interaction. So while it is true that I am a Ruby specialist, I don't like that label. I don't like it because it's very limiting. My goal is to solve problems and quite often Ruby is a great tool for that, but for some problems, it is not. So I need a job where my expertise is helpful but would not limit my desire to learn new approaches, languages and skills.</p>

<p>And this is why I will soon start working as a <em>Code Alchemist in the LivingSocial R&amp;D's lab</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://merbist.com/2011/06/10/sayonara-sony/livingsocial-2/"><img src="http://merbist.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/livingsocial1.png" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>That might be a shocker at first glance. Going from working on video games to working for a daily-deal startup? It doesn't seem like a very smart career move. To be honest, that was my first reaction. But LivingSocial's VP of engineering is <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/chadfowler">Chad Fowler</a> (the author of The Passionate Programmer, mentioned earlier) and its VP of R&amp;D is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Kilmer_(programmer">Rich Kilmer</a>), InfoEther's cofounder and recognized mad-scientist-coder. I've known Chad and Rich for many years, meeting at tech conferences that they organized or were invited to give talks to, and even getting to hack on some projects with Rich. So when they approached me to join them at LivingSocial, I wanted to know more about their own motivations, why I would be a good fit and how the company/job would rate against my list of criteria. We had long and honest discussions and the result is that I am excited to soon be working with one of the best teams I know of. More concretely, I will be working with <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/rich_kilmer">Rich</a>, <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/wbruce">Bruce</a> and <a href="http://twitter.com/#!/go">Michael</a> in helping LivingSocial revolutionize the local market. LivingSocial is a fast growing and successful company with a strong focus on creating a great experience for both customers and merchants. The company's vision is well defined and the desire to change the world the way we know it is palpable. Most of the founders have a technical background, they value good engineering practices and have created a nice, positive company culture. Chad has some really awesome, passionate and talented engineers on his team (too many to mention), for whom I have a lot of respect and with whom I look forward to working with.  I also value the fact that LivingSocial trusts and values me enough to let me work remotely. This is very important for me because it shows that my new employer really wants to work with me, trusts me but also is willing to embrace the challenges of having a remote team if that's what's needed to create the "right team". After looking more deeply at what I need and what LivingSocial is, I believe that I can assist LivingSocial in making a very positive change to the way small businesses around the world are run. And I am looking forward to this.</p>

<p> </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Ruby movement - art & programming]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2010/09/27/the-ruby-movement-art-programming/"/>
    <updated>2010-09-27T19:12:51+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2010/09/27/the-ruby-movement-art-programming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I wrote a guest blog post for <a href="http://rubylearning.com/blog/about/">Satish Talim</a> over at <a href="http://rubylearning.com/blog/">RubyLearning.org</a></p>

<p>You can read it <a href="http://rubylearning.com/blog/2010/09/28/the-ruby-movement/">there</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://rubylearning.com/blog/2010/09/28/the-ruby-movement/"><img src="/images/posts/the-ruby-movement.jpg" title="The Ruby Movement by Matt Aimonetti" alt="The Ruby Movement by Matt Aimonetti" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Discussion with a Java switcher]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2010/08/22/discussion-with-a-java-switcher/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-22T17:18:55+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2010/08/22/discussion-with-a-java-switcher</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the past 6 months, I have had regular discussions with an experienced Java developers who switched to Ruby a couple years ago. Names have been changed to protect the guilty but to help you understand my friend 'Duke' better, you need to know that he has been a developer for 10 years and lead many complicated, high traffic projects. He recently released two Ruby on Rails projects and he has been fighting with performance issues and scalability challenges.</p>

<p>Duke is a happy Ruby developer but he sometimes has a hard time understanding why things are done in a certain way in the Ruby community. Here are some extracts from our conversations. My answers are only based on my own experience and limited knowledge. They are probably not shared by the entire  community, feel free to use the comment section if you want to add more or share your own answers.</p>

<h2>Threads / Concurrency</h2>

<p><strong>Duke:</strong> Why does the Ruby community hate threads so much. It seems to be a taboo discussion and the only answer I hear is that threads are hard to deal with and that Ruby does not have a good threading implementation. What's the deal there? If you want concurrent processing, threads are important!</p>

<p><strong>Me:</strong> This is a very good question and I think there are two main reasons why threads and thread safety are not hot topics in the Ruby world. First, look at Ruby's main implementation itself. If you are using an old version of Ruby (pre Ruby 1.9) you don't use native threads but green threads mapping to only 1 native thread. Ilya has a great (yet a bit old) <a href="http://www.igvita.com/2008/11/13/concurrency-is-a-myth-in-ruby/">blog post explaining the difference</a>, why it matters and also the role and effect of the Global Interpreter Lock (GIL). Also, even though Rubyists like to say that they live in the edge, most of them still use Ruby 1.8 and therefore don't really see the improvements in Ruby 1.9 nor yet understand the potential of <a href="http://ruby-doc.org/core-1.9/classes/Fiber.html">fibers</a>.</p>

<p>The other part of the explanation is that the Rails community never really cared until recently. Yehuda Katz recently wrote a <a href="http://yehudakatz.com/2010/08/14/threads-in-ruby-enough-already/">good article on thread safety</a> in Ruby and if you read his post and <a href="http://dpaste.de/5xyG/raw/">Zed Shaw's comment</a> you will understand a bit better the historical background. As a matter of fact, the current version of Rails is not multi-threaded by default and developers interested in handling concurrent requests in one process should <a href="http://api.rubyonrails.org/classes/Rails/Configuration.html#M002069">turn on this option</a>. Thread safety appeared for the first time in Rails 2.2 but from what I saw, most people still don't enable this option. There are many reasons for that. First, enabling thread safety disables some Rails features like automatic dependency loading after boot and code reloading. A lot of Rails developers take these two features for granted and don't understand that they are technically "hacks" to make their lives easier. I do believe a lot of Rails developers don't understand how threads, thread safety, concurrency, blocking IO and dependencies work. They care about getting their app done and meet their deadlines. They usually use and know Rails without paying too much attention to how Rails extends Ruby. Imagine what would happen if their code wasn't thread safe and Rails wasn't not using a global lock by default. Now you see why things are not exactly as you expect and also why some Rubyists are getting excited about new projects like <a href="http://nodejs.org/">node.js</a> which takes a different approach.</p>

<p>The other thing to keep in mind is that at least 90 to 95% of the Rails apps out there don't get more than a dozen requests/second (a million requests/day). You can scale that kind of load pretty easily using simple approaches like caching,  optimize your DB queries, load balancing to a couple servers. As a matter of fact, compared to the amount of people using Rails on a daily basis, only a very little amount of people are struggling with performance and scalability like you do. This is not an excuse but that explains why these people don't care about the things you care about.</p>

<h2>Rails is slow</h2>

<p><strong>Duke:</strong> I don't understand why Rails developers are not more concerned about the speed/performance penalty induced by Rails.</p>

<p><strong>Me:</strong> Again, Rails is fast enough for the large majority of developers out there. As you know, as a developer you have to always make compromises. The Rails team always said that development time is more expensive than servers and therefore the focus is on making development easier, faster and more enjoyable. However to get there, they have to somewhat sacrifice some performance. What can be totally unacceptable for you is totally fine for others and your contribution is always welcome. This is probably the root cause of the things you don't like in Rails. Rails was built for startups, by startup developers and you don't fall in this category. People contributing new features and fixes are the people using Rails for what it is designed to do. There is no real 'Enterprise' support behind Rails and that might be why you feel the way you feel. Since you find yourself questioning some key Rails conventions and you are struggling with missing features, it looks  to me that you chose the wrong tool for the job since you don't even use 70% of the Rails features and are dreaming of things such 3 tier architecture. <a href="http://sinatrarb.com">Sinatra</a> might be a better fit for you if you want lower level control, less conventions and less built-in features.</p>

<h2>Object allocation / Garbage Collection</h2>

<p><strong>Duke:</strong> I recently read that Twitter was spending <a href="http://blog.evanweaver.com/articles/2009/10/21/object-allocations-on-the-web/">20% of its request cycles in the GC</a>, am I the only finding that concerning?</p>

<p><strong>Me:</strong> Most people don't realize how the GC works and what it means to allocate objects since Ruby does that automatically. But at the same time, most of these people don't really see the affect of the Garbage Collection since they don't have that much traffic or they scale in ways that just skips their Ruby stack entirely. (Or they just blame Ruby for being slow)</p>

<p>If you are app deals with mainly reads/GET requests, using HTTP caching (Rails has that built-in) and something like Varnish/<a href="http://rtomayko.github.com/rack-cache/">Rack-cache</a> will dramatically reduce the load on your server apps. Others don't investigate their issues and just add more servers. As mentioned in a <a href="http://merbist.com/2010/07/29/object-allocation-why-you-should-care/">previous post</a>, some libraries like Builder are allocating LOTS more objects than others (Nokogiri), use the existing debugging tools to see where your object allocations occur and try to fix/workaround these. In other words, Ruby's GC isn't great but by ignoring its limitations, we made things even worse. My guess is that the GC is going to improve (other implementations already have better GCs) and that people will realize that Ruby is not magic and critical elements need to be improved.</p>

<h2>Tools</h2>

<p><strong>Duke:</strong> I really have a hard time finding good tools to help scale my apps better and understand where I should optimize my code.</p>

<p><strong>Me: </strong>It is true that we area lacking tools but things are changing. On top of the built-in tools like <a href="http://ruby-doc.org/core-1.9/classes/ObjectSpace.html">ObjectSpace</a>, <a href="http://ruby-doc.org/core-1.9/classes/GC/Profiler.html">GC::Profiler</a>, people interested in performance/debugging are working to provide the Ruby community with their expertise, look at <a href="http://memprof.com/">memprof</a> and <a href="http://rubyforge.org/projects/ruby-debug/">ruby-debug</a> for instance. Of course you can also use tools such as <a href="http://ruby-prof.rubyforge.org/">Ruby-prof</a>, <a href="http://kcachegrind.sourceforge.net/html/Home.html">Kcachegrind</a>, <a href="http://valgrind.org/">Valgrind</a> and <a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/gdb/">GDB</a>. (1.9.2 was <a href="http://github.com/yugui/ruby/tree/feature/dtrace">scheduled to have DTrace support</a> but I did not check yet). Maybe you should be more explicit about what tools you miss and how we could solve the gap.</p>

<h2>ActiveRecord</h2>

<p><strong>Duke:</strong> ActiveRecord doesn't do what I need. How come there is no native support for master/slave DBs, sharding, DB view support is buggy,  suggested indexes on queries is not built-in and errors are not handled properly (server is gone, out of sync etc..)?</p>

<p><strong>Me:</strong> You don't have to use ActiveRecord, you could use any ORM such as <a href="http://sequel.rubyforge.org/">Sequel</a>, <a href="http://datamapper.org/">DataMapper</a> or your own. But to answer your question, I think that AR doesn't do everything you want because nobody contributed these features to the project and the people maintaining ActiveRecord don't have the need for these features.</p>

<h2>What can we do?</h2>

<p>We, as a community, need to realize that we have to learn from other communities and other programming languages, this kind of humorous graph is unfortunately not too far from reality.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/G7WyP.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p>Bringing your expertise and knowledge to the Ruby community is important. Looking further than just our own little will push us to improve and fulfill the gaps. Let the community know what tools you are missing, the good practices you think we should be following etc...</p>

<p>Take for instance <a href="http://nodejs.org/">Node.js</a>, it's a port of <a href="http://wiki.github.com/eventmachine/eventmachine/">Ruby's EventMachine</a> / <a href="http://twistedmatrix.com/trac/">Python's twisted</a>. There is no reasons why the Ruby or Python versions could not do what the Javascript version does. However people are getting excited and are jumping ship. What do we do about that? One way would be to identify what makes node more attractive than EventMachine and what needs to be done so we can offer what people are looking for. I asked this question a few weeks ago and the response was that a lot of the Ruby libraries are blocking and having to check is too bothersome. Maybe that's something that the community should be addressing. Node doesn't have that many libraries and people will have to write them, in the mean time we can make our libs non-blocking. Also, let's not forget that this is not a competition and people should choose the best tool for their projects.</p>

<p>Finally, things don't change overnight, as more people encounter the issues you are facing, as we learn from others, part of the community will focus on the problems you are seeing and things will get better. Hopefully, <strong>you</strong> will also be able to contribute and influence the community to build an even better Ruby world.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ruby object allocation & why you should care]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2010/07/29/object-allocation-why-you-should-care/"/>
    <updated>2010-07-29T23:47:50+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2010/07/29/object-allocation-why-you-should-care</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I was tasked with finding how to optimize a web application with heavy traffic. The application (a Rails 2.3.x app) gets about 3 million requests per hour and most of these requests cannot really be easily cached so they go through the entire stack.</p>

<p>This is probably not the case of most web apps out there. None the less, my findings my help you understand Ruby better and maybe think differently about memory management.</p>

<p>This is certainly not an advanced GC blog post, I will try to keep it as simple as possible. My goal is to show you how Ruby memory allocation works and why it can affect your app performance and finally, how can you avoid to allocate to many objects.</p>

<h2>Ruby memory management.</h2>

<p>Rubyists are quite lucky since they don't have to manage the memory themselves. Because developers are lazy and Matz developed his language for people and not machine, memory is managed "magically". Programming should be fun and managing memory isn't really considered fun (ask video game developers or iOS programmers ;)).</p>

<p>So in Ruby, the magical memory management is done by a Garbage Collector. The GC's job is to run and free objects that were previously allocated but not used anymore. Without a GC we would saturate the memory available on the host running the program or would have to deallocate the memory manually. Ruby's GC uses a conservative, stop the world, mark-and-sweep collection mechanism.  More simply, the garbage collection runs when the allocated memory for the process is maxed out. The GC runs and blocks all code from being executed and will free unused objects so new objects can be allocated.</p>

<p>Joe Damato did a great talk on that matter during last RailsConf</p>

<p><a href="http://www.scribd.com/doc/32718051/Garbage-Collection-and-the-Ruby-Heap">Garbage Collection and the Ruby Heap</a></p>

<p>The problem is that Ruby's GC was not designed to support hundred thousand objects allocation per second. Unfortunately, that's exactly what frameworks like Ruby on Rails do, and you might contribute to the problem too without even knowing it.</p>

<h2>Does it really matter?</h2>

<p>I believe it does. In my case improving the object allocation means much better response time, less servers, less support and less headaches. You might think that servers are cheaper than developers. But more servers mean more developer time spent fixing bugs and more IT support. That's why I think, memory management is something Ruby developers should be aware of and should take in consideration, especially the ones writing frameworks, libraries or shared code.</p>

<p>I am using Ruby 1.9 so I could not profile my Rails 2.x app using <a href="http://memprof.com/">memprof</a>, instead I wrote a <a href="http://github.com/mattetti/GC-stats-middleware">simple and basic middleware</a> that keeps track of the memory allocation/deallocation and GC cycles during a web request (Ruby1.9 only). One of my simple Rails2 actions (1 DB call, simple view) is allocating 170,000 objects per requests. Yes, you read right: 170k objects every single request. At 3 million requests/hour, you can imagine that we are spending a LOT of time waiting for the GC. This is obviously not 100% Rails fault as I am sure our code is contributing to the problem. I heard from the memprof guys that Rails was allocating 40k objects. I decided to check Rails3.</p>

<p>After warming up, a basic Rails3 'hello world' app clocks at about <strong>8,500 objects allocated per request</strong>, forcing the GC to run more or less every 6 requests. On my machine (mac pro) the GC takes about 20ms to free the objects. A Rack 'hello world' app clocks at <strong>7 objects</strong> per request and a Sinatra app at <strong>181 objects</strong>. Of course you can't really compare these different libraries/frameworks but that gives you an idea of the price you pay to get more features.</p>

<p>One thing to remember is that the more objects you allocate, the more time you "lose" at code execution. For more developers, it probably doesn't matter much, but if you should still understand that concept especially if you decide to contribute to the OSS community and offer patches, libraries, plugins etc...</p>

<h1>What can I do?</h1>

<p>Be aware that you are allocating  objects, for instance something as simple as 100.times{ 'foo' } allocates 100 string objects (strings are mutable and therefore each version requires its own memory allocation).</p>

<p>Make sure to evaluate the libraries you use, for instance switching a Sinatra XML rendering action from Builder to Nokogiri XML Builder saved us about 12k object allocations (Thanks Aaron Patterson). Make sure that <strong>if </strong>you are using a library allocating a LOT of objects, that other alternatives are not available and your choice is worth paying the GC cost. (you might not have a lot of requests/s or might not care for a few dozen ms per requests). You can use memprof or one of the many existing tools to check on the GC cycles using load tests or in dev mode. Also, be careful to analyze the data properly and to not only look at the first request. <a href="http://twitter.com/akeem">Someone</a> sent me <a href="http://memprof.com/dump/4c52503c7fdeb62cff000001">this memory dump</a> from a Rails3 'hello world' with Ruby 1.8.7 and it shows that Rails is using <a href="http://memprof.com/dump/4c52503c7fdeb62cff000001/detail?where=%7B%7D">331973 objects</a>.  While this is totally true, it doesn't mean that 330k objects are created per request. Instead that means that 330k objects are currently in memory. Rubygems loading already allocate a lot of objects, Rails even more but these objects won't be GC'd and don't matter as much as the ones allocated every single request. The total amount of memory used by a Ruby process isn't that important, however the fluctuation forcing the GC to run often is. This is why my middleware only cares about the allocation change during a request. (The GC should still traverse the entire memory so, smaller is better)</p>

<p>The more object allocation you do at runtime/per request, the more the GC will need to run, the slower your code will be. So this is not a question of memory space, but more of performance. If your framework/ORM/library/plugin allocates too many objects per request maybe you should start by reporting the problem and if you can, offer some patches.</p>

<p>Here are some hints about memory allocation:</p>

<p>Creating a hash object really allocates more than an object, for instance {'joe' => 'male', 'jane' => 'female'} doesn't allocate 1 object but 7. (one hash, 4 strings + 2 key strings) If you can use symbol keys as they won't be garbage collected. However because they won't be GC'd you want to make sure to not use totally dynamic keys like converting the username to a symbol, otherwise you will 'leak' memory.</p>

<p>Looking at a GC cycle in the Rails3 hello world example shows what objects get deallocated:</p>

<blockquote><p>GC run, previous cycle was 6 requests ago.</p></blockquote>

<p>GC 203 invokes. (amount of cycles since the program was started)
Index   1</p>

<p>Invoke Time(sec)   25.268</p>

<p>Use Size(byte)   4702440</p>

<p>Total Size(byte)   7307264</p>

<p>Total Object   182414</p>

<p>GC Time(ms) 22.35600000000204090611</p>

<h2>56322 freed objects.</h2>

<p><strong>[78%] 44334 freed strings.</strong>
<strong>[7%] 4325 freed arrays.</strong>
[0%] 504 freed bignums.
[1%] 613 freed hashes.
[0%] 289 freed objects.
<strong>[5%] 3030 freed parser nodes (eval usage).</strong></p>

<p>I did not list all the object types but it's pretty obvious that the main issue in the case of Rails is string allocation. To a certain extend the allocated arrays and the runtime use of eval are not helping either. (what is being eval'd at runtime anyway?)</p>

<p>If you use the same string in various place of you code, you can "cache" them using a local var, instance variable, class variable or constant. Sometimes you can just replaced them by a symbol and save a few allocations/deallocations per request. Whatever you do tho, make sure there is a real need for it. My rule of thumb is that if some code gets exercised by 80% of the requests, it should be really optimized and avoid extra allocations so the GC won't slow us down.</p>

<h2>What about a better GC?</h2>

<p>That's the easy answer. When I mentioned this problem with Rails, a lot of people told me that I should use JRuby or Rubinius because their GC were much better. Unfortunately, that's not that simple and choosing an alternative implementation requires much further research and tests.</p>

<p>But what annoys me with this solution is that using it is not solving the issue, it's just working around it. Yes, Ruby's GC isn't that great but that's the not the key issue, <strong>the key issue is that some libraries/frameworks allocate way too many objects</strong> and that nobody seems to care (or to even know it). I know that the Ruby Core Team is working on some optimizations and I am sure Ruby will eventually get an improved GC. In the meantime, it's easy to blame Matz, Koichi and the rest of the core team but again, it's ignoring that the root cause, totally uncontrolled memory allocation.</p>

<p><strong>Maybe it's time for us, Rubyists, to think a bit more about our memory usage.</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Au Revoir Rails community]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2010/06/04/au-revoir-rails-community/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-04T17:45:20+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2010/06/04/au-revoir-rails-community</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Time really flies!</p>

<p>Back in December 2005, Ruby on Rails 1.0 was released to the masses. I remember that was when I first got interested in Rails. Six months later, I was doing Rails development full time.</p>

<p>Rails pushed me to contribute to the project, to write plugins, to improve my Ruby knowledge, to release gems and to become a better engineer overall. I then joined the <a href="http://merbivore.com">Merb project</a>, focusing on problems I was facing in the various client projects I had back then.</p>

<p>The competition between Rails and Merb turned into a constant confrontation, splitting the Ruby community into two camps. A resolution was later achieved by merging the two teams and focusing our energy on Rails 3. This is how I became a part of the Activism team with <a href="http://blog.envylabs.com/">Gregg</a> and <a href="http://railscasts.com/">Ryan</a>. In this new role I was given the opportunity to meet lots of different people from various backgrounds and different communities. I really had a lot of fun.</p>

<p>However, things have changed for me. I won't be at Rails Conf 2010 because in a few weeks I will become a father for the first time. And with that, an obvious priority shift. My day job working on <a href="http://community.modnation.com/">Playstation games</a> is also quite time consuming and the little free time I manage to get to work on my own projects is spent on my <a href="http://macruby.labs.oreilly.com/">MacRuby book</a>. The disconnect between the Rails community and myself is probably more evident now than ever. The challenges encountered by most Railists are so different from the ones I face daily that I think others would do a much better job than I at advocating for Rails. So this is why I believe it's time for me to step away from the Rails community, kick back and relax (and get ready to change a lot of diapers).</p>

<p>This is an "<a href="http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/au+revoir">au revoir</a>", not an "<a href="http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/adieu">Adieu</a>". I will continue to keep an eye on Rails 3 and the fast growing ecosystem.</p>

<p>I will still be writing Ruby for a living and will hopefully keep contributing to the projects I use. And I plan to keep on attending to Ruby conferences around the world just as soon as my kid is old enough to travel with me ;)</p>

<p>Finally, with the imminent release of Rails 3, I hope to see even more people stand up and advocate for Ruby on Rails the way Gregg Pollack, Ryan Bates and many others have done so far.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing an open licensed book]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2010/05/09/writing-an-open-licensed-book/"/>
    <updated>2010-05-09T22:40:06+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2010/05/09/writing-an-open-licensed-book</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To celebrate last week's release of <a href="http://www.macruby.org/blog/2010/04/30/macruby06.html">MacRuby 0.6</a>, O'Reilly and I started publishing the draft of my MacRuby book online: <a href="http://macruby.labs.oreilly.com/">http://macruby.labs.oreilly.com/</a></p>

<p>I started thinking about working on "<a href="http://macruby.labs.oreilly.com/">MacRuby: The Definitive Guide</a>" last year when I realized that the project had a great future but there was a serious lack of documentation. With the support of the MacRuby team, I worked on a table of contents and a pitch. The next step was to decide what we wanted to do with the book.</p>

<p>I know a lot of technical book authors and most of them will tell you the same thing: if you think that you are going to make money writing a book, you are wrong. Even if your book sells well, because of the time invested in writing the book, you are probably better off doing consulting work and charging by the hour.</p>

<p>So since day one, I knew that this project would not make me rich. The goal was to share knowledge not to reimburse my mortgage or save California from bankruptcy. While publishing a web book is great, distribution is quite limited, especially if you try to reach people outside of your network. That's why I decided to start talking to a few publishers. Most publishers I talked to were interested in working on the book, however they were not really keen on publishing a <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/us/">Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-No Derivative</a> licensed book.</p>

<p>Let me explain why I think releasing technical books under a CC license is important. As you might know (or have figured out by now), I am not a native English speaker. I actually learned my first English words thanks to the computer my dad had at home. The problem when you don't live in an English speaking country and you want to learn about the cutting edge technology is that you have to understand English.  Thanks to the Internet, learning and practicing English is now much easier that it used to be. However, if you want to have access to books, most of the time you have to wait until someone translates the book and publishes it in your country or you have to manage to get an English version delivered to your country. This is often a pain because of national credit card limitations, international delivery restrictions etc... If you manage to find a way to get a copy, the book ends up costing a lot of money.</p>

<p>What does that mean in practice? Most of the technical books are first available in the English speaking western world, then slowly translated and/or distributed around the world. By the time you get a legal copy in Bolivia, Algeria or Vietnam, a new edition is probably out in the US probably because the technology evolved. Maybe that explains some of the book piracy worldwide?</p>

<p>Think about it for a minute: knowledge is power and time is money. And what do we do? We delay knowledge distribution. This is why I am a big fan of the <a href="http://khanacademy.org/">Khan Academy</a> and its awesome free online courses.</p>

<p>Turns out <a href="http://oreilly.com/">O'Reilly</a> shares my vision and has already published a lot of books under various open licenses: <a href="http://oreilly.com/openbook/">http://oreilly.com/openbook/</a> I was also interested in publishing the content of my book ASAP so people could access it right away even though there would be lots of typos and missing content. This is also something O'Reilly has already done with the <a href="http://books.couchdb.org/relax/">CouchDB</a> and the <a href="http://labs.oreilly.com/ofps.html">Scala</a> books.</p>

<p>Talking with <a href="http://twitter.com/janl">Jan Lehnardt</a> about his experience working with O'Reilly on the <a href="http://books.couchdb.org/relax/">'CouchDB: The definitive guide'</a> book, I realized that we seem to have some shared interests. I contacted Jan's editor and we decided to start working on the MacRuby book. The book will be available later on in all the usual commercial formats and I hope people will show their support so O'Reilly will be encouraged in their choice to continue publishing CC licensed book. At the end of the day, purchasing a CC licensed book helps supporting the authors, the publishers but also all the people who can't have access to the latest technical books.</p>

<p>Finally, working on a book is not an easy thing, especially when you have to write it in a language that's not yours. But I have to say that the community support has been amazing. Even <a href="http://daringfireball.net/linked/2010/05/03/macruby-aimonetti">John Gruber sent a fireball my way</a>. And since the announcement was made, I have received a lot of <a href="http://macruby.labs.oreilly.com/comments/feed?id=book">comments</a>, tweets, emails etc... It is very encouraging and it gives me the motivation needed to work on the book after a long work day.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I did it wrong]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2010/03/15/i-did-it-wrong/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-15T23:50:49+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2010/03/15/i-did-it-wrong</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Ruby community is a well known for at least two things: <strong>being </strong><a href="http://pragprog.com/press_releases/the-passionate-programmer">passionate</a><strong> and being </strong><a href="http://www.bruisin-ales.com/beerblog/wp-content/uploads/2008/09/stoneintro.gif">arrogant</a> .
Two characteristics that often go together but I am not going to defend or justify anything in this post, instead I will try to reflect on my own experience and will share with you my own view point.</p>

<p><a href="http://merbist.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/doing_wrong_coaster_2.jpg"><img src="http://merbist.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/doing_wrong_coaster_2-225x300.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Very much like the Ruby community, I am also quite passionate and can be arrogant at times. A few months back I was in Brazil for <a href="http://www.railssummit.com.br/en/pages/home">RailsSummit</a> and I was chatting with <a href="http://twitter.com/dchelimsky">David Chelimsky</a> after a nice evening with the <a href="http://www.railssummit.com.br/en/pages/home">RailsSummit</a> attendees. I was thinking about how cool it was to have people from various non-Ruby communities to come to a Ruby community and share their experience and knowledge while observing the ways we do things with Ruby.</p>

<p>David and I got to talk about technical evangelism, how <a href="http://rspec.info/">RSpec</a> became very popular, the whole <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merb">Merb</a> vs <a href="http://rubyonrails.org/">Rails</a> situation which turned into Rails3, as well as <a href="http://www.macruby.org/">MacRuby</a> and <a href="http://www.apple.com/">Apple</a>. I was interested by the fact that I couldn't remember David ever saying something bad about test/unit or trying to tell others they were doing it wrong. Instead, he has always tried showing why people might be potentially interested by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RSpec">RSpec</a>.</p>

<p>As an early RSpec adopter, I often thought that people were wrong not to use the solution that <em><strong>I</strong></em> thought was the best. As part of the Merb 'propaganda', we spent a lot of time comparing Merb with Rails and showing why Merb might be better for you and why you were doing it wrong if you would fit in Merb's target and still use Rails.</p>

<p>Even before that, I remember thinking that if you were not using Ruby, you were doing it wrong. PHP &amp; Java developers were, for me, just developers who did not know any better (and I thought that Python-ers were just too lazy to learn a "better" language that takes OOP seriously ;)).</p>

<p><a href="http://merbist.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/doing_it_wrong_coaster.jpg"><img src="http://merbist.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/doing_it_wrong_coaster-300x218.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Since then, things have changed. I have gotten involved with other projects, met different people and maybe, just maybe, matured a little bit. Going back to the discussion I had with David, he pointed out to me how often people talk about a piece of technology or an idea to just quickly conclude: <strong>"it sucks"</strong> and it has got even worse lately with the '<a href="http://www.doingitwrong.com/">you're doing it wrong</a> ' meme.</p>

<p>Basically, we judge people's actions without knowing them or even having a clue about the problem they are facing and we just tell them that if they don't do like us, they are wrong. If they are not using this plugin or this gem, they are doing it wrong, and if they are using this other one that sucks, they are also doing it wrong. Also, be careful, something that's hot today will probably turn out to be 'the suck' soon enough, keep up with what the cool kids tweet about ;)</p>

<p>But of course, this is something human and much bigger than the Ruby community. Look at the whole SQL/NoSQL <a href="http://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=1163039">pseudo fight</a> and you will notice the same attitude. Look at the editors war, look at the OS war or even look at the TV with shows like '<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Marriage%20Ref">Marriage Ref</a>' making money off of people wanting to prove their partner that he/she is doing it wrong. But that's also the root problem of most religion wars and even the motivation for some people to go 'invade/colonize' other countries to eventually force their world vision upon them.</p>

<p>I realize the irony of writing of blog post to tell my readers that telling others that they are doing it wrong is, in itself, fundamental wrong, but maybe next time you think something sucks or is totally wrong, you might want to try to understand the motivation behind why some people decided to go this way. I know I will personally try harder.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How and why I joined the "suit people"]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2010/02/02/how-and-why-i-joined-the-suit-people/"/>
    <updated>2010-02-02T11:19:26+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2010/02/02/how-and-why-i-joined-the-suit-people</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is now official: I have traded my freedom &amp; home office for a job title, an Aeron chair in a cubicle and a 401K.</p>

<p>I received my new employee package and, in less than a week, I will officially become a full-time employee at <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sony_Computer_Entertainment_of_America"> SCEA</a> (Sony Computer Entertainment America).</p>

<p>I'm going to work in the PlayStation department, working on PS3, PS2 and PSP game titles developed by <a href="http://www.naughtydog.com/">various</a> <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SCE_Studio_San_Diego">game</a> <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sony_Computer_Entertainment_Worldwide_Studios">studios</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://merbist.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/02/sony_playstation_32.jpg"><img src="http://merbist.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/02/sony_playstation_32-300x206.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<h3>Why 'o why?</h3>

<p><em>Why leave behind a happy life of indie contracting to join corporate America?</em></p>

<p>For many reasons actually:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>A Team</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>Being a consultant I have been working with other independent consultants and existing teams. Nonetheless, I really miss being part of a stable team which grows together and learns from each other as we go through new projects and maintain old ones.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Long term plan</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>As a consultant, I usually start projects or "rescue" existing projects. I work on them for a little while and then move on. It's exciting and rewarding but you don't really pay the consequences of your mistakes. You usually don't have to maintain the code you wrote and you rarely deal with the mistakes <em>you</em> made.</p>

<p>It sounds good, nobody likes to maintain the crappy awesome code they wrote 2 years ago and most developers love working on new stuff. But at the same time, to become a better engineer you need to learn from you mistakes and assuming responsibility for your bad decisions is part of the process.</p>

<p>It might sound weird, but I'm actually excited to work on long term projects and feel some sort of ownership over the projects. Having to support games for many years means that I'd better not mess up the implementation. And if I do, I hope I'll quickly learn from my mistakes.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Avoiding burn out</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>There is no secret: when you are passionate about what you do, you have a hard time stopping and taking a break. I'm a recovering workaholic and it's really hard for me to say no when I'm presented the possibility to work on interesting projects. I love what I do and I keep writing code even after I'm done with client work.</p>

<p>The problem is that this can start me on the slippery slope to isolating myself from friends, family and people who don't share the same passion. I'm really lucky that my wife is a geek and loves hanging out at conferences, looking at code and playing with my buggy prototypes. But still, I spend too much time "playing" with my computer and I just can't manage my free time wisely.</p>

<p>Having a full time position will hopefully help me put boundaries and will hopefully teach me to disconnect from work.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Exciting projects</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>Hey, let's be honest, how many geeks do you know don't want to work in the video game industry? By the way, if you don't have a PS3, they are now at $299 and on top of getting an awesome console you get a blue ray player! (And no, I do not receive any bonuses or commissions for mentioning the console or promoting it in my blog. I had to pay for my own like everyone else.)</p>

<h3>Corporate America? Are you going to write Java now?</h3>

<p><img src="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1412/1264424156_24f4571b10.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>No, I'm mainly going to stick to the language I love: <strong>Ruby</strong>.
From time to time I will probably use other languages here and there, but that usually makes me love Ruby even more. The reality is that Ruby's power and flexibility seem to be appreciated by SCEA, which makes sense when you have tight deadlines and a lot of new technologies to deal with. Ruby is a perfect match!</p>

<p>As you can guess, I can't go into any detail about how and why Sony uses Ruby, but let me just say that while games are still usually written in C++, they are becoming more and more interactive and need to communicate with game servers where some logic operates. Game players also need to interact with other gamers as well as check their gaming progress online, as well as the progress of the players around them etc... Basically, outside of the game engine and the console SDK, there is a lot of potential for Ruby.</p>

<p>Coming back to Corporate America, I have to say that I've known my future manager for a few years now. He's always been a fervent Ruby advocate and has introduced lots of teams to the happiness of Ruby &amp; Rails development. He's also a great developer who's contributing patches to major projects and has a bunch of cool stuff on github. To give you an idea, my job description mentions Rails, Merb, Sinatra, CouchdB, MongoDB, Redis, AWS. All these Ruby technologies are actually already used in production or are being seriously evaluated.</p>

<p>I'm also really looking forward to join the existing team. I know I'm going to love working with a bunch of awesome developers coming from various backgrounds.</p>

<p>Those who know me, know that I'm not a morning person. And while your typical office job is categorized as '9-5', don't feel too bad for me. I will be joining the video game product department, and morning people are rather rare in these kinds of groups ;)</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>I'm really excited about this opportunity. For me, it is proof again that the Ruby revolution took place and that the Enterprise is evolving. Of course, time will tell if I am right, but I am quite confident.</p>

<p>Also, Sony is always looking for new, talented people who want to push the entertainment world to the next level. Feel free to keep in touch with me if you are interested in joining the fun.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Amazon Kindle 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2010/01/05/amazon-kindle-2/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-05T17:36:12+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2010/01/05/amazon-kindle-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For Noël, my wife got me a new toy: <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0015T963C?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=merbist-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B0015T963C">the Amazon Kindle 2</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0015T963C?tag=merbist-20"><img src="http://placeholder.apture.com/ph/360x280_AmazonProduct/" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2>Kindle vs Nook</h2>

<p>Before my wife bought what became my new favorite gadget, we checked on the Barnes &amp; Noble Nook.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm5.static.flickr.com/4012/4176062087_704a33b9fd_m.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>The primary problem with the Nook was that it was out of stock. That pushed me to dig deeper and really compare both devices.</p>

<p>The Nook had some interesting features like wifi, small color screen and the book lending feature.</p>

<p>However, I don't really care about a small, clunky extra color screen since I just want to read books. The wifi is nice... but what am I going to do with it? Lending books is a cool feature, but this feature isn't available for all books and is apparently seriously limited.</p>

<p>So I decided to focus on what I really needed instead of what I could use.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>The main purpose of an e-book is reading, page loading should be fast and the user experience should be at least as good as when reading a 'real' book.</p></li>
<li><p>I need to be able to have a great choice of books and if possible in multiple languages.</p></li>
<li><p>I would like to be able to read the <a href="http://www.safaribooksonline.com/">safarionline</a> books that I can access online.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>From what I read almost everywhere, the nook is slow and a bit buggy (it's a first generation after all) and doesn't come with a web browser. I also checked on the ebooks available on Amazon and Barnes &amp; Noble. Amazon has way more ebooks and that's really what motivated my decision. The other thing is that Amazon is present world wide and I expect them to start selling more ebooks in French and Spanish.</p>

<p>The other thing that pushed me to buy a Kindle was the fact that I know so many people having one and being so pleased. During a recent trip to San Diego, <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/in/yehudakatz">Yehuda Katz</a> told me about how much he loves his Kindle and he recommended a book to read. I started reading the book on my iPhone (using kindle for iPhone) and was really wanted a bigger screen.</p>

<h2>Kindle vs iTablet</h2>

<p>A lot of people asked me why I didn't wait for the big announcement of the iTablet because it might be a Kindle killer.</p>

<p>First, the iTablet is currently just a rumor and if we would believe the rumor, the iTablet will sell around $1,000 vs $250 for a kindle. The tablet will probably do a lot of cool stuff my e-reader can't do... but I don't care I chose the kindle because I wanted a simple device to read book and only do that. Actually, the  kindle + iphone combo works great for me. I used to read a lot but because I have been moving so many times I started reading less because I always get rid of my books. Also, when traveling a lot, carrying your books with you is a pain. (especially now that most airlines charge you per bag)</p>

<h2>Kindle and tech books/documentation.</h2>

<p>If you want a kindle to read tech books, don't get a 6", get the kindle DX instead. Even though the 6" natively supports PDF files, the text is usually too small and the Kindle doesn't support zooming (yet).</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0015TCML0?tag=merbist-20"><img src="http://placeholder.apture.com/ph/360x280_AmazonProduct/" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>The DX is perfect to read PDFs because the ratio matches the print expectations. I was thinking about converting all the Cocoa docs to a kindle friendly format since the kindle supports search etc.. But the truth is that it's not worth it. The display on a 6" screen is clunky, it just doesn't feel right. I didn't try any of the pragprog ebooks but something tells me they will just look better on the DX.</p>

<p>Since I wanted a kindle to read books and not browse tech documentation, I'm still really happy with 6".</p>

<p>If you also have kindle or are planning on buying one soon, here are two books I've been enjoying reading:</p>

<p>[caption id="" align="alignleft" width="280" caption="Flashforward by Robert J. Sawyer"]<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Flashforward-ebook/dp/B002NANLCE/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;s=books&amp;qid=1262741423&amp;sr=8-1-catcorr"><img src="http://ecx.images-amazon.com/images/I/51qntNYMMEL._SL500_AA246_PIkin2,BottomRight,-12,34_AA280_SH20_OU01_.jpg" alt="" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>[caption id="" align="alignright" width="280" caption="The Talent Code by Daniel Coyle"]<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Talent-Code-Greatness-Grown-ebook/dp/B0026OR1UK/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;s=books&amp;qid=1262741566&amp;sr=1-1"><img src="http://ecx.images-amazon.com/images/I/41CluL6Fo9L._SL500_AA246_PIkin2,BottomRight,-13,34_AA280_SH20_OU01_.jpg" alt="" /></a>[/caption]</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Ruby Revolution, take II]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/11/16/the-ruby-revolution-take-ii/"/>
    <updated>2009-11-16T08:05:55+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/11/16/the-ruby-revolution-take-ii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[caption id="attachment_638" align="alignright" width="300" caption="Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi"]<img src="http://merbist.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/GANDHI.jpg" alt="Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi" />[/caption]</p>

<p>My recent '<a href="http://merbist.com/2009/11/09/the-ruby-revolution-is-over">Ruby revolution being over</a>' blog post generated quite a <a href="http://merbist.com/2009/11/09/the-ruby-revolution-is-over/#comments">lot of comments</a>.
Let's be honest, I did not expect less from the readers.</p>

<p>However, I noticed three types of reactions I would like to address:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>It was not a Ruby revolution, it was a Rails revolution</p></li>
<li><p>The revolution has stalled due to no major enterprise backing</p></li>
<li><p>The revolution will only be over when we will reach a greater adoption</p></li>
</ul>


<p>First of all, as <a href="http://merbist.com/2009/11/09/the-ruby-revolution-is-over/#comment-817">Joe correctly mentioned</a>, for me, the revolution is not about specifics or individuals. It's really about the big picture.</p>

<p>The influence Ruby had and still has on the IT world seems to be undermined by some.
Ruby is a dynamic, truly Object Oriented programming scripting language <strong>designed for humans first</strong>.
The real paradigm shift is in the fact that Ruby was designed to make programming fast, enjoyable and easy instead of being optimized for the machines running it.
This is for me the essence of the revolution and it is meant to transcend the scope of the Ruby language.</p>

<p>The way I see it, Yukihiro Matsumoto (Matz) is more of an artist than a technician. He had a vision for software development. <strong>Programming languages cannot be optimized/designed for both machines and humans, the language designer has to choose which one he wants to privilege.</strong></p>

<p>Most programming languages believe that it's up to the programmer to make an extra effort since he is smarter and easier to optimize than a machine. Matz questioned this approached and decided to turn things around. The result is one of the reasons why developers seem to just fall in love with Ruby.</p>

<h3>It was not a Ruby revolution, it was a Rails revolution.</h3>

<p>I am not denying that there <strong><em>also</em></strong> was a Rails revolution.
But if you look at it, Rails and its revolution are a direct effect from Ruby's revolution.
One might argue that it is actually an extension of Ruby's philosophy. But what is Rails if not a web framework designed to make web development fast, easy and enjoyable?
Without Ruby there would not have been Rails and that was my point, the underlying revolution comes from the language itself.</p>

<h3>The revolution has stalled due to no major enterprise backing.</h3>

<p>That's an interesting comment. It is true that .NET and Java are still dominating the enterprise world. But let's be clear, Ruby was not designed to please "suit people".
And to this day, there is still a strong feeling, from some individuals against the enterprise.
In the past, DHH openly said that he did not care nor wanted to hear about the enterprise, more recently, Obie Fernandez, during one of his talks said: <a href="http://blip.tv/file/2733212">"Fuck the enterprise"</a> (49:39).
<strong>But the truth is that Ruby and the so called enterprise, both, are changing.</strong>
The smart people in the enterprise world saw potential in Ruby and decided to give it a chance. An easy way to include Ruby's philosophy without breaking the fragile enterprise equilibrium was to inject Ruby in the midst of well known and respected technologies such as Java and .NET. The enterprise can now use "re-branded Ruby versions" with "new taste or 'improved' flavor" like JRuby, Scala, groovy, IronRuby.
I work for some enterprise clients and I can tell you that they 'also' use Ruby. Mainly because developers love the language.
Microsoft, Apple and SAP investing in their own implementation of the language is yet another example that the enterprise recognizes the value of Matz's work.
Nobody can blame them to try to make Ruby fit more their requirements.
So, at the end of the day, Ruby is not the #1 enterprise language and Rails isn't used by the large majority of enterprise web apps, but that is NOT the point. Ruby has influenced the enterprise and we will see its effects for many years.</p>

<h3>The revolution will only be over when we will reach a greater adoption</h3>

<p>Saying that is missing the point entirely. A revolution is a step towards a situation change. Things don't change right away after a revolution. It takes a long time for mentalities to evolve and for people to change their habits.
The consequences of a revolution are to be studied over the decades following the event. Take smalltalk for instance. Smalltalk adoption was not that great, however it brought a paradigm shift that directly influenced languages such as Ruby, Python and Objective-C.
So, again, do not focus on the adoption but instead look at the influence of the Ruby revolution and the ripple effect around it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Ruby revolution is over]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/11/09/the-ruby-revolution-is-over/"/>
    <updated>2009-11-09T00:10:16+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/11/09/the-ruby-revolution-is-over</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/a7/Eug%C3%A8ne_Delacroix_-_La_libert%C3%A9_guidant_le_peuple.jpg/300px-Eug%C3%A8ne_Delacroix_-_La_libert%C3%A9_guidant_le_peuple.jpg" alt="Liberté guidant le peuple - Eugene Delacroix posted by Matt Aimonetti" /></p>

<p>According to wikipedia, a <strong>revolution</strong> (from the latin <em>revolutio</em>, "a turn around") is a fundamental change in power or organizational structures that takes place in a relatively short period of time.</p>

<p>Somehow, I believe this is exactly what Ruby has done in the programming world, especially with the help of Rails. Over the last few years, Ruby lead a mini revolution in the midst of software development. Thanks to Ruby, developers now look at software development differently. One thing for sure, it pushed DHH to write Rails and then convinced thousands of people to develop Ruby based applications on a daily basis.</p>

<h3>How did it happen?</h3>

<p>Let's take a look at history of revolutions. Some people get frustrated their situation, they try to find workarounds until it's just too much and the revolution kicks in.</p>

<p>Ruby came up with a new holistic perspective on things. Unlike most other programming languages, one of the main key value of Ruby is that writing code should feel right for the developer. You feel good about it because the language was written for humans and not machines. Basically, the language was designed to make you productive because it's designed to please you.</p>

<p>As people were discovering web 2.0, Ruby also came with an opinionated framework, pushing for productivity, testing, simplicity and elegance. People started to see a new way of doing things and it quickly became the new, cool technology. Rails became a buzz word, developers were hired to work on cool projects, and books were selling by the thousands.</p>

<h3>What did it change?</h3>

<p>If you ask my mom, she would probably say: nothing, except that now my son works from his home office and he seems to really enjoy what he does for living.</p>

<p>Relatively speaking, Ruby did not change the way we work or live. However, I believe that it has influenced many software developers around the globe. Why else do you think that companies like Microsoft, Apple or SAP are working on their own implementation of the Ruby language?</p>

<p>When I first discovered Ruby, I was amazed at how "right" it felt, at how much fun it was to write code using its syntax and idioms. Now, if I don't get that feeling when testing a programming language, I think there is something wrong.</p>

<p>The Ruby community also revived the Agile/XP world. Testing being a strong value of the community, we spent a lot of time discussing TDD, BDD, integration test as well as other practices such as pair programming, code review, sprints etc..</p>

<p>A few years ago, when people were asking me what programming language I would write their app in, I would reply Ruby and had to explain what it was, why it is great and would have to answer a lot of questions from potential clients. Nowadays, people don't even argue, sites like hulu.com, twitter.com, yellowpages.com and many others are written in Ruby and it's just part of the tools known to work very well.</p>

<h3>The revolution is over!</h3>

<p>Yes, Ruby made it's revolution and the world "has changed". But a real movement doesn't die after its revolution, that's actually when it has to be strong and defend its values.</p>

<p>This doesn't mean that Ruby is dead or that Rails is "passé". To the contrary, Ruby imposed itself as a new valued and respected player, a new standard if you will.</p>

<p>Ruby is certainly not the "new kid in the block"anymore nor the "popular kid", however lots of older kids seem to want to have her on their team. (.NET, Java, Objective-C can all use Ruby)</p>

<p>The TDD + Ruby combo doesn't surprise anyone anymore and the Enterprise is slowly but surely adopting Ruby. Ruby is now just getting better, tools and libraries are improving and the amount of users is growing.</p>

<p>Certainly the Ruby community is still small compared to other software developer communities, but the fundamental change was done and we are now working on improvement and keeping things running smoothly, growing and getting new ideas inspired by our experience and other communities.</p>

<p>Long live Ruby!</p>

<p><a href="http://merbist.com/2009/11/16/the-ruby-revolution-take-ii/">See my follow up.</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RailsSummit - The future of Ruby and Rails]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/10/23/railssummit-2009/"/>
    <updated>2009-10-23T10:17:45+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/10/23/railssummit-2009</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>During <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/danicuki/sets/72157622452350763/">Rails Summit2009</a> in São Paulo, Brazil Matt
Aimonetti gave a talk entitled <em>The future of Ruby and Rails</em>.</p>

<h2>Description of the talk:</h2>

<p>Plans for Rails 3 and tour of the various Ruby implementations.</p>

<h2>Slides</h2>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="4f90acc391b203001f002180" data-ratio="1.3333333333333333" src="http://matt.aimonetti.net//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>


<h2>Video</h2>

<p>The video of this talk is available <a href="http://blip.tv/agaelebe/ruby-rails-future-matt-aimonetti-rails-summit-2009-2748035">here</a>.</p>

<h2>Blog post</h2>

<p>I have had the opportunity to go to and speak at many conferences but this year was the first time I had the chance to go to <a href="http://railssummit.com.br">RailsSummit</a> in São Paulo, Brazil.</p>

<p>I was really looking forward to this trip and I have to say it went beyond my expectations. I had heard really good things from people such as the <a href="http://www.phusion.nl/">Phusion guys</a> (Ninh &amp; Hongli), Gregg Pollack and others.</p>

<p>For those who don't know, RailsSummit is one of the biggest, if not the biggest, Ruby event in Latin America. It's organized yearly by <a href="http://www.locaweb.com.br/">Locaweb</a>, the #1 hosting company in Brazil (props to Akita &amp; Cristiane for their work).</p>

<p><img src="http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2761/4027342992_789777fd03_m_d.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>As part of my involvement in the Ruby community I have met a lot of Brazilians always willing to help and especially giving time to translate content. (A good example would be the <a href="http://wiki.rubyonrails.org/pt/start">Portuguese version of the Rails wiki</a> or <a href="http://blog.plataformatec.com.br/">José Valim</a> GSOC contribution) However, I did not realize how fast Rails was growing over here.</p>

<p>To come back to the conference, I have to say it was one of the best conference I have gone to. Chad Fowler, who gave the opening keynote, later told me that it reminded him of the first Ruby conferences in the US . For me, what made a huge difference was the fact that it was a very positive conference. People were happy to be here, eager to share and you could feel the passion. Unfortunately, I missed the first few Ruby conferences, but I can totally imagine how must have been. Passionate people, not trying to push their products but instead, share the cool stuff they've been working on. This is exactly the feeling I had during this conference.</p>

<p>Maybe it's because I don't understand Portuguese well enough or maybe it's just a cultural thing, but the people at the conference were just super friendly and always willing to help. I was really glad to meet those who have been using some of my work, some new people to Ruby and people who don't do Ruby but were just interested in knowing what was going on in the Ruby world.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2719/4027357802_1082f38090.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>The schedule was pretty packed and the discussions very interesting, you could certainly feel the excitement in the air. Ruby seems to catching up quickly over there. Brazilian Rubyists seem to be very pragmatic and a good illustration of that was certainly made by <a href="http://improveit.com.br/en">Vinicus Teles</a>, Brazil Agile XPert, who shared tips on how to release a successful product.</p>

<p>I stayed a few days after the conference and went to visit the Rubyists in Rio. Rio is a great city. It has some of the best soccer players in the world and some seriously talented software developers. Ruby &amp; Rails are not just the new trendy startup secret to success, companies like globo.com, currently the largest TV network in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latin_America">Latin America</a> and the fourth largest in the world, also started using Ruby and Rails. I had the opportunity to visit their office and meet their teams. It's very exciting to see how they use Agile/XP and Ruby and how they seem to be so successful. But I will keep that for another post.</p>

<p>Overall, even though the actual traveling to/from Brazil was a bit long, RailsSummit was a blast. I really hope to be able to come back next year, and by then, hopefully my Portuguese will have improved.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blog status]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/08/30/blog-status/"/>
    <updated>2009-08-30T16:35:01+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/08/30/blog-status</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had people asking me how come I was not blogging as much lately. Well, on top of being really busy, I have been blogging on other blogs such as the <a href="http://weblog.rubyonrails.org/">official Rails blog</a>.</p>

<p>There aren't a lot of Merb news, we are waiting for Carl and Yehuda to sign out on the 1.1 release and will hopefully soon start the migration work to Rails3. If you want more news about Rails3, check <a href="http://yehudakatz.com/">Yehuda's blog</a> and the <a href="http://weblog.rubyonrails.com/">official Rails blog</a>. Lots of exciting things are coming up.</p>

<p>Finally, if you are planning on upgrading your Mac to Snow Leopard, <a href="http://weblog.rubyonrails.org/2009/8/30/upgrading-to-snow-leopard">these instructions</a> are also valid for all Ruby developers on an Intel mac.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ruby, Rack and CouchDB = lots of awesomeness]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/07/27/ruby-rack-and-couchdb-lots-of-awesomeness/"/>
    <updated>2009-07-27T13:49:20+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/07/27/ruby-rack-and-couchdb-lots-of-awesomeness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the weekend, I spent some time working on a Ruby + Rack +CouchDB project. Three technologies that I know quite well but that I never put to work together at the same time, at least not directly.  Let's call this Part I.</p>

<p>Before we get started, let me introduce each component:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruby%20%28programming%20language%29">Ruby</a> : if you are reading this blog, you more than likely know at least a little bit about, what I consider, one of the most enjoyable programming language out there. It's also a very flexible language that lets us do some interesting things. I could have chosen Python to do the same project but that's a whole different topic. For this project we will do something Ruby excels at: reopening existing classes and injecting more code.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://rack.rubyforge.org/">Rack</a>: a webserver interface written in Ruby and inspired by <a href="http://www.wsgi.org/wsgi/">Python's WSGI</a>. Basically, it's a defined API to interact between webservers and web frameworks. It's used by most common Ruby web frameworks, from Sinatra to Rails (btw, Rails3 is going to be even more Rack-focused than it already is). So, very simply put, the webserver receives a request, passes it to Rack, that converts it, passes it to your web framework and the web framework sends a response in the expected format (more on Rack later).</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://couchdb.apache.org/">CouchDB</a>: Apache's document-oriented database. RESTful API, schema-less, written in Erlang with built-in support for map/reduce. For this project, I'm using <a href="http://github.com/mattetti/couchrest">CouchRest</a>, a Ruby wrapper for Couch.</p></li>
</ul>


<h2>Goal: Log Couch requests and analyze data</h2>

<p>Let's say we have a Rails, Sinatra or Merb application and we are using CouchRest (maybe we are using CouchRest and ActiveRecord, but let's ignore that for now).</p>

<p>Everything works fine but we would like to profile our app a little and maybe optimize the DB usage. The default framework loggers don't support Couch. The easy way would be to tail the Couch logs or look at the logs in <a href="http://janl.github.com/couchdbx/">CouchDBX</a>. Now, while that works, we can't really see what DB calls are made per action, so it makes any optimization work a bit tedious. (Note that Rails3 will have some better conventions for logging, making things even easier)</p>

<p>So, let's see how to fix that. Let's start by looking at Rack.</p>

<h2>Rack Middleware</h2>

<p>Instead of hacking a web framework specific solution, let's use Rack. Rack is dead simple, you just need to write a class that has a <em>call</em> method.
In our case, we don't care about modifying the response, we just want to instrument our app. We just want our middleware to be transparent and let our webserver deal with it normally.</p>

<p>Here we go ... that wasn't hard, was it? We keep the application reference in the @app variable when a new instance of the middleware is created. Then when the middleware is called, we just call the rest of the chain and pretend nothing happened.</p>

<p>As you can see, we just added some logging info around the request. Let's do one better and save the logs in CouchDB:</p>

<p>Again, nothing complicated. In our rackup file we defined which Couch database to use and we passed it to our middleware (we change our initialize method signature to take the DB).
Finally, instead of printing out the logs, we are saving them to the database.</p>

<p>W00t! At this point all our requests have been saved in the DB with all the data there, ready to be manipulated by some map/reduce views we will write. For the record, you might want to use the bulk_save approach in CouchDB which will wait for X amount of records to save them in the DB all at once. Couch also let's you send new documents, but only save it to the DB every X documents or X seconds.</p>

<p><img src="http://img.skitch.com/20090726-ebmpgjtrc6x8239ia69kmri1rt.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>As you can see, our document contains the timestamps and the full environment as a hash.</p>

<p>All of that is nice, but even though we get a lot of information, we could not actually see any of the DB calls made in each request. Let's fix that and inject our logger in CouchRest (you could apply the same approach to any adapter).</p>

<p>Let's reopen the HTTP Abstraction layer class used by CouchRest and inject some instrumentation:</p>

<p>Again, nothing fancy, we are just opening the module, reopening the methods and wrapping our code around the <em>super</em> call (for those who don't know, <em>super</em> calls the original method).</p>

<p>This is all for Part I. In Part II, we'll see how to process the logs and make all that data useful.</p>

<p>By the way, if you make it to <a href="http://www.railssummit.com.br/">RailsSummit</a>, I will be giving a talk on Rails3 and the new exciting stuff you will be able to do including Rack based stuff, CouchDB, MongoDB, new DataMapper etc..</p>

<p><a href="http://railssummit.com.br/"><img src="http://railssummit.com.br/images/banners/en_souPalestrante_210x60.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ruby authentication of CouchDB requests]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/07/13/ruby-authentication-of-couchdb-requests/"/>
    <updated>2009-07-13T13:00:13+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/07/13/ruby-authentication-of-couchdb-requests</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://couchdb.apache.org/">CouchDB</a> is an awesome technology. I'm lucky enough to work on quite a big project where we decided to switch from MySQL to Couch for various reasons.</p>

<p>One of the many things I like with Couch is that it handles attachments and can replicate them as well as serve them for you using the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erlang%20%28programming%20language%29">Erlang</a> based builtin webserver. (you can load balance your dbs and do some other really cool stuff)</p>

<p>Let's take a use case. Let's imagine that you have a web app with logged in users. Every user can have their own avatar.</p>

<p>No big deal, you get the user to upload his/her avatar to your app and add it to the user document in the database. To serve it from the database, you just need to create a proxy in nginx/apache and redirect the virtual avatar url to the protected DB making sure the request is a GET request.</p>

<p>Add to that a caching solution like <a href="http://varnish.projects.linpro.no/">varnish</a> or <a href="http://www.igvita.com/2008/02/11/nginx-and-memcached-a-400-boost/">memcached module for nginx</a> and all your db goodies get cached and served by the cache (server/client) until they get modified.</p>

<p>Now, the problem is when you want to serve authorized attachments. Let's imagine that we want to let our users upload private files, files that should be accessible only by the owner or users designated by the owner.</p>

<p>In this case, a simple <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nginx">nginx</a> rewrite wouldn't work. We need to authorize attachment requests. Here is a cool way of doing that using nginx and merb's router. (Expect Rails3 router to do the same).</p>

<p>Let's start by setting up nginx and create a proxy for couchdb:</p>

<p>Now that this is done, we are going to use Merb's awesome router to handle the incoming requests. The cool part of this is that we won't be dispatching requests so, going through the router is almost free. (check on the Merb router benchmarks for more info).  Let's edit our router and set a special route for our assets.</p>

<p>We are using a deferred route which gets executed instead of dispatching the request.</p>

<p>If the attachment route is being matched then we are checking what environment we are currently running in. If we are in production or staging environment then we are sending back a rack response to the webserver. The response is just a forward to the proper couchdb document behind the proxy. Of course, before allowing that to happen, we could authenticate the logged in user, log the request and do a couple of other things. You have full access to your models from the router, so authenticating a session isn't a big deal. You could even create temporarily urls like AWS s3 does.</p>

<p>If we are not in production or staging mode, then just redirect the request to couch since we assume you have access to the local db. This way, your asset urls will be working in production and dev. In real life, you'll want to apply the authorization before choosing how to deliver the document/attachment tho as you want it work the same way in development and production.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Compiled hello world with MacRuby]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/07/12/compiled-hello-world-with-macruby/"/>
    <updated>2009-07-12T11:53:53+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/07/12/compiled-hello-world-with-macruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To celebrate the amazing <a href="http://lists.macosforge.org/pipermail/macruby-devel/2009-July/002062.html">work being done by Laurent Sansonetti on MacRuby</a> here is a hello world using the new <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LLVM">LLVM</a> based compiler.
<code>
$ echo "p ARGV.join(' ').upcase" &gt; hello_world.rb
$ macrubyc hello_world.rb -o macruby_says
$ ./macruby_says hello world
"HELLO WORLD"
</code></p>

<p>Note that to achieve this result, you need to be using the experimental branch of MacRuby and have LLVM installed. (check the <a href="http://svn.macosforge.org/repository/ruby/MacRuby/branches/experimental/README.rdoc">readme</a> available in MacRuby's repo).</p>

<p>Let's quickly look at what we just did.
We created a single line ruby script that takes the passed arguments, joins them and print them uppercase.
Then, we compiled our script into a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mach-O">Mach-O</a> object file and produce an executable.</p>

<p>Here is an extract from Laurent's latest status report:</p>

<blockquote><p>Produced executables embed all the compiled Ruby code as well as MacRuby, statically.
It can be distributed as is and does not depend on anything MacRuby or LLVM at runtime.
The Ruby source code is compiled into native machine code (same process as we do at runtime with the JIT compiler), so it's also a good way to obfuscate the source code.
The final binary looks like an Objective-C binary (except that it's larger)</p></blockquote>

<p>Don't expect to compile Rails just yet, it's still in a preliminary stage.</p>

<p>The final release you should let you pick one of the 2 compilation modes:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>normal mode</strong>: full ruby specs, compile down to machine code and use LLVM at runtime. (recommended for desktop/server apps)</li>
<li><strong>full mode</strong>: no full ruby spec support, no runtime code generation, no LLVM. ("very light application and/or if the environment does not support runtime code generation" (<em>hint-hint)</em>)</li>
</ul>


<p>As you can see, <a href="http://macruby.org">MacRuby</a> is moving forward and the experimental branch should soon move to trunk.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Engendering Strong Reactions]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/04/28/on-engendering-strong-reactions/"/>
    <updated>2009-04-28T17:16:03+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/04/28/on-engendering-strong-reactions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To start with, I would like to make it clear to everyone that I do sincerely care about the larger gender issues that my presentation touched off.  I have also replied and otherwise corresponded with everyone who has contacted me about my presentation, just as I have tried to reply to all of the blog posts that have been brought to my attention.  At this point, however, it is clear that this issue has grown too large to be resolved through one-on-one contact, hence this public statement.</p>

<p>I have made a specific point of exchanging emails with most of the bloggers who addressed the gender issue, and I did so because I care about minority involvement in our community.  I cared about this issue well before GoGaRuCo or this particular presentation, despite what anyone might think to the contrary, running the presentation past my wife/business partner and other colleagues well before I gave my talk.  They, at least, understood the goals of my presentation, which were to leaven an otherwise dry topic with humor.  It genuinely was not my intention to cause offense.  People may be driven by personal choice or cultural background to take offense at any number of things, of course, but I think there is always a clear difference between trying to offend people vs people choosing to take offense.</p>

<p>My view is that offending someone is walking up to them and saying: "You suck, your code sucks and your partner's code sucks!".
That is not what I did in my talk.  In the case of my talk, people knew what to expect, they <em>picked</em> the talk, and were warned by the organizers before I started that I would be using imagery potentially offensive to some.  The topic of my talk was obvious, and I would have hoped that people who were likely to be offended would have simply chosen not to attend my talk or read my slides on the internet.  It's like complaining that television has too much material unsuitable for children, yet not taking steps to limit their viewing of it.  You can't have it both ways.</p>

<p>Now that I have explained my view point as clearly as I can, I would also like to express my sincere regret that this situation has brought bad publicity to Rails and the loss of one of the Activism team members.  I understand how people who are concerned about gender equality could have taken my presentation badly and misjudge my intentions, if they did not know me.</p>

<p>In the same way, people have been rather quick to judge the entire Ruby/Rails community based on my presentation and the comments of a few people. I have noticed, for example, a lot of comments making sweeping generalizations about Americans, Republicans, women, Ruby, Rails, men etc.. leading to an exchange of insults, things getting personal, and everybody feeling the need to fuel the flames by sharing their own opinion in public.  While there is nothing wrong with sharing your approval or disapproval, I think it has also contributed to blowing this entire thing completely out of proportion.  I would like to ask people to step back and reflect upon whether we are contributing anything useful to the discussion.</p>

<p>We can argue forever about morals, professionalism, ethics, respect, etc., though this is all a distraction from the real problem that was raised by Sarah, namely that we have very few minorities in the Ruby community, especially women.  Minorities do need to be more represented!</p>

<p>So, instead of continuing an increasingly pointless debate about my slides, I would like to encourage the community to look further and see how we can change things.
Education, outreach, and self-censorship are certainly some of the options available.   Please read <a href="http://www.quirkey.com/blog/2009/04/27/the-ghetto-of-the-mind/">Aaron's blog post</a> and see how you might make a difference.</p>

<p>For those who still want to talk with me, I will be at the <a href="http://en.oreilly.com/rails2009/public/schedule/detail/8772">RailsConf devchix's discussion panel</a> and more importantly, if you care about Rails Activism and you want to see things evolve, be sure to come to our <a href="http://en.oreilly.com/rails2009/public/schedule/detail/9047">Birds of Feather discussion of Rails Activism</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> Some people thought I wasn't clear enough about my position and I therefore tweeted the following: <a href="http://twitter.com/merbist/status/1661486850">"I obviously made a mistake. I didn't mean to offend anyone but since I did, I failed."</a></p>

<p><strong>Update 2:</strong> Kirrily Robert wrote a <a href="http://infotrope.net/blog/2009/08/05/action-and-reaction-on-avoiding-offense/">very insightful article</a>. Borrowing her words, I'd like to reiterate that "It genuinely was not my intention to marginalize or exclude anyone from my talk or from the Ruby community, nor to make them feel uncomfortable."</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Merb 1.1 delayed]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/04/14/merb-11-delayed/"/>
    <updated>2009-04-14T09:02:45+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/04/14/merb-11-delayed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We made the decision to slightly delay the release of Merb 1.1 as we ended up changing the scope of what we wanted to make available in the 1.1 release. If you have been following our releases, you know that this is not something we usually do, but we strongly believe that this is actually something that will save us time for the next release.</p>

<p>The big themes for 1.1 are full Ruby 1.9 support and Rails3 compatibilty: action-orm(previously called active-orm) and the new router.</p>

<p>While on one hand, Ruby 1.9 work is 99% done (we still have a couple of failing specs with action-args) and action-orm just needs to be merged in, on the other hand, the new router currently does more than what we initially planned for. It actually covers stuff we scheduled for 1.2.</p>

<p>Here is a quick preview of what Carl has been working on:</p>

<p>Merb's router is now extracted into a rack middleware library and a bunch of features to try to get "mountable apps" working in Merb 1.1 have been added.</p>

<p>The proof of concept has been submitted to the Rack development mailing list and the draft is available at:
<a href="http://github.com/carllerche/rack-router/tree/master">http://github.com/carllerche/rack-router</a></p>

<p>Merb, CloudKit, Sinatra and more than likely Rails3 should be using this new rack based router. This is a huge step for the Ruby community!</p>

<p>Here is the abstract explained by carl:</p>

<blockquote><p>Conceptually, rack-router allows you to create a two way map between HTTP requests and Rack applications. It is built as a piece of middleware that takes in a set of routes.
When a request comes in, the router will compare that request against the set of routes until it finds one that matches. It then calls the associated rack app.
It can also generate URL's that you can use to link to other mountable apps.
It also goes quite a bit further and attempts to make reusing rack applications completely painless (what we are tentatively calling "mountable apps").</p></blockquote>

<p>For more information, check the <a href="http://groups.google.com/group/rack-devel/browse_thread/thread/41334bce83cb173f">mailing list thread</a>.</p>

<p>Now that the proof of concept has been accepted, the new implementation needs to be optimized to match the speed of the previous router. Currently the new router is pretty slow compared to 1.x router.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[merb progress]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/02/06/merb-progress/"/>
    <updated>2009-02-06T14:09:27+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/02/06/merb-progress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As they say: fail early, fail often. Well, I've been failing to blog recently, but as always I have some good excuses ;)</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://yehudakatz.com/">Yehuda</a> has been blogging a lot about the work done on the merge.</p></li>
<li><p>I have been busy working on probably the <a href="http://github.com/mattetti/couchrest">awesomest CouchDB Ruby DSL/ORM</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>I have been working with the <a href="http://weblog.rubyonrails.com/activism">Rails Activists</a> on the <a href="http://newwiki.rubyonrails.org">new wiki</a> and many other projects.</p></li>
<li><p>My sister is visiting from France :)  (most of my free time is not spent in front of a computer anymore :p)</p></li>
<li><p>I've been playing with MacRuby (see the end of the post)</p></li>
<li><p>Ohh and spent some time maintaining Merb and preparing 1.0.9</p></li>
</ul>


<h2>Merb 1.0.9</h2>

<p>Merb 1.0.8.1 has some issues with the merb-cache settings set in init.rb being called twice when you use some Rake tasks. (rake db:automigrate for instance).The problem is due to the fact that the rake tasks load the dependencies twice:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Merb rake file loads all of your app dependencies and their rake tasks. (for instance rake db:automigrate is a rake task coming from merb_datamapper)</p></li>
<li><p>The task you are invoking might start merb itself to load the models etc.. and starting Merb reloads the dependencies.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Dependencies have the option to have a require block. A require block is a Proc that gets called when the dependency is being required. In the case of 1.8.1, we added a default block to set merb-cache. The problem was that the block was being set and called twice and merb-cache was complaining that the default cache was already setup.</p>

<p>To fix this issue we worked on a band-aid type solution (read: kinda evil but ok). Even if you start Merb multiple times, the init.rb file will no only load once and the dependency require blocks will only be called once. However, in the case of merb-cache, the setup block is being called everytime you go through the bootloader. That's why we added a verification on the block itself. In the long term, we are going to fix things nicely and optimize the way merb-cache loads.</p>

<p>We also addressed some other issues. Some people have been pointed out issues with some merb-helpers and patches were provided by the community (thanks a lot).</p>

<p>Talking about patches, we also accepted a patch fixing a small problem with merb-auth and some open-id servers.</p>

<p>Ruby 1.9.1: We started going through all the different places were things are not compatible yet, most of the work that needs to be done right away is focused on the router. Carl has been working on that and you can check his branch to see how we are doing. During the next week we will try to get things ironed out, we still don't know how we are going to deal with the fact that action-args uses parsetree which is not 1.9.1 compatible.</p>

<p>The upcoming version also gets a brand new feature: memory monitoring by the merb master process. The master process checks that the workers don't use too much memory ( you can set what you consider beign too much memory using Merb::Config[:max_memory]) and if one of the workers reaches the limit, it does a kill -1. It then waits a configured amount of seconds (defaults to 5) then kill using -9.</p>

<p>Finally, we also fixed a bunch of tiny issues.</p>

<p>1.0.9 should be released in the next few days.</p>

<hr />

<h2>MacRuby</h2>

<p>Finally, because for those interested in MacRuby here are my slides from last night's SDRuby meetup:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/mattetti/macruby-when-objectivec-and-ruby-meet?type=presentation">MacRuby - When objective-c and Ruby meet</a></p>

<p>View more <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/">presentations</a> from <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/mattetti">Matt Aimonetti</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meet the merbists: Hampton Catlin]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/01/06/meet-the-merbists-hampton-catlin/"/>
    <updated>2009-01-06T12:13:37+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2009/01/06/meet-the-merbists-hampton-catlin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://farm1.static.flickr.com/156/379744976_8f241811fe_m.jpg" alt="Matt Aimonetti interviewing Hampton Catlin" /></p>

<p>Meet today's merbist: <a href="http://hamptoncatlin.com/">Hampton Catlin</a></p>

<p>I'm personally looking forward to seeing Hampton's work migrated to Rails 3 in a few months.</p>

<p> </p>

<p><strong>Matt Aimonetti</strong>: Hi Hampton, could you please introduce yourself and tell us what you do for a living.</p>

<p><strong>Hampton Catlin: </strong>I'm Hampton Catlin. I'm "The Haml Guy" as I'm apparently termed all the time when introduced. I'm an early Rails hacker who has done a lot more than Haml, but whatever. These days, I'm doing a ton of iPhone development and am currently heading Wikimedia's efforts for a new mobile platform... based on Merb!</p>

<p> </p>

<p><strong>Matt Aimonetti</strong>: How did you get started with Ruby, what's your background?</p>

<p><strong>Hampton Catlin</strong>: Well, everyone is welcome to laugh. But Slashdot introduced me to Ruby. I got into it about two months before Rails because the hotness (it was an obscure project at the time) and I grabbed a copy of the Pickaxe and never looked back. Prior to that I was working a crappy job getting people coffee at a bank. And then prior to that I was doing research for Nasa at my university with Java beuwolf clusters. It sounds fancier than it was.</p>

<p> </p>

<p><strong>Matt Aimonetti:</strong> You chose to learn and use Merb, could you please let us know why and how that happened?</p>

<p><strong>Hampton Catlin: </strong>I had known of Ezra for a while and Yehuda. And so when I heard about the project, I was very interested. At the time I was looking forward to using a "Rails Light". Of course, we know Merb is much more than that, but that was the original attraction.</p>

<p>Also, at some point I got really upset by the use of global variables in both of the frameworks, so I did some major patching to Merb to change over to module based constants. Aka, Merb.root instead of MERB_ROOT. I was ranting about it enough that I decided to do something about it. Also, I did some patches that messed up Merb with some weird documentation stuff. Sorry, Ezra.</p>

<p> </p>

<p><strong>Matt Aimonetti</strong>: Do you have some Merb projects available online we can look at? what was your experience so far?</p>

<p><strong>Hampton Catlin</strong>: My most successful iPhone app (which was recently purchased by Wikimedia) was an app to browse Wikipedia. I chose Merb because I knew that I wanted something a little more bare bones than Rails, and it turned out to be a really good choice. And now, I'm getting a chance to extend that work into an entire platform for Wikimedia mobile. I am still looking for help with it....<a href="http://github.com/hcatlin/wikimedia-mobile/tree/master">http://github.com/hcatlin/wikimedia-mobile/tree/master</a>
Its not live yet with wikipedia, but that's the code that you can help with! :)</p>

<p> </p>

<p><strong>Matt Aimonetti</strong> What is your favorite aspect of the Merb framework?</p>

<p><strong>Hampton Catlin: </strong>Its modular design. Its as complex or as simple as you would like it to be. Also, its easy to run Haml, and the more people that use Haml, the harder my nipples get.</p>

<p> </p>

<p><strong>Matt Aimonetti</strong> Could you please mention an aspect of Merb you hope to see being improved in the near future?</p>

<p><strong>Hampton Catlin</strong>: Honestly, everyone is wild about gems, but I'm not particularly. I find gem management a bit cumbersome. I'm most likely doing something wrong or not doing it the right way. But yeah, I still find it cumbersome. I'd like to pair the excellent Gem support with better library creation support. I think both are needed. I don't want to throw stuff in my /lib folder or randomly in my project. I want some structure and some simplicity. Somewhere between plugins and base libraries. I think this is where Merb <em>could</em> shine.</p>

<p>Also, resource handling. I wrote make_resourceful for Rails and I keep needing to do something similar for Merb. m_r is not very popular because I haven't really put much time into spreading the word. Mostly, I just use it. However, there are about 60 other Rails developers in the world that use it extensively. So, its a small, close-knit group of developers using the tool. And, I think something like it could be much more elegantly mixed into Merb. Obviously its a plug-in, but I think its a low hanging fruit. "current_object" as a method should ALWAYS be around when its logical.</p>

<p> </p>

<p><strong>Matt Aimonetti</strong> Thank you for your time. Anything else you would like to add?</p>

<p><strong>Hampton Catlin</strong>: Buy my book. Buy my book. Buy my book. Buy my book. Buy my book. Buy my book. Buy my book. Buy my book. Buy my book. Buy my book. Ok, not really. My book isn't very good. But, I just wanted to make a "The Critic" reference.</p>

<p> </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rails vs Merb Â¿drama?]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2008/11/15/rails-vs-merb-drama/"/>
    <updated>2008-11-15T19:07:46+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2008/11/15/rails-vs-merb-drama</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>That's official, according to Twitter the fight has started.</p>

<p>In this corner, weighing in at XXX LOC, from 37signals in the white trunks: <strong>Rails</strong> and in this other corner,Â  weighing in at YYY LOC from Engine Yard: <strong>Merb</strong>!</p>

<p>[caption id="attachment_247" align="alignright" width="150" caption="Yehuda Katz"]<a href="http://merbist.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/11/yehuda-katz.jpg"><img src="http://merbist.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/11/yehuda-katz-150x150.jpg" alt="Yehuda Katz" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>[caption id="attachment_246" align="alignleft" width="150" caption="David Heinemeier Hansson"]<a href="http://merbist.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/11/dhh.jpg"><img src="http://merbist.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/11/dhh-150x150.jpg" alt="David Heinemeier Hansson" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>I wish I had a more aggressive photo of Yehuda, but oh well...</p>

<p>So people love drama, from American Idol to the Elections without forgetting Survivor, Heroes and other TV shows. Few weeks ago there was a tentative from Giles to create some controversy but he did not really work so well. The last big drama we had in the Ruby community was Zed and his infamous blog post...</p>

<h2>The plot</h2>

<p>Once upon a time, in a world where .NET, JAVA and PHP were ruling the internet development world, a not so well known programming language was getting more and more traction in the far east. Ruby, as it was known in Japan, only had very little documentation in English and real ninjas had to translate docs from <em>obscure</em> Japanese writings in order to become enlightened. Nevertheless, a courageous Danish student named David decided to build an application called <a href="http://www.basecamphq.com/">basecamp</a> using this "exotic" language. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Heinemeier_Hansson">David</a> decided to extract a framework from his work for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/37_signals">37signals</a>. He called his framework "<a href="http://rubyonrails.org/">Ruby on Rails</a>" and offered it to the world under the MIT license. Pretty quickly, as <a href="http://www.ruby-lang.org/en/">Ruby</a> was getting more popular in the West, people looked at "Rails" and loved the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Model-view-controller">MVC architecture</a>, the conventions over configuration, testing framework and especially the language: <a href="http://www.ruby-lang.org/en/">Ruby</a>.</p>

<p>As Rails was getting popular, a man from Polish descent known as <a href="http://brainspl.at/">Ezra Zygmuntowicz</a> and who was working for <a href="http://www.engineyard.com/">Engine Yard</a> got frustrated with some of Rails limitations. He needed something simpler, easier and faster. In fact he just needed a Mongrel handler, a way to process a request really quickly without going through then entire stack and without slowing down the main app. That's how Ezra started <a href="http://merbivore.com">Merb</a>.</p>

<p>Let's fast forward 2 years. The year is 2008, the place is Orlando, Florida. <a href="http://yehudakatz.com">Yehuda Katz</a>, Merb's lead developer announces the 1.0 release of a Ruby web framework started 2 years earlier by Ezra. The framework's selling points are: performance, modularilty, flexibilty.Â  In the mean time other Ruby frameworks were developed such as <a href="https://code.whytheluckystiff.net/camping/">camping</a>, <a href="http://sinatra.rubyforge.org/">Sinatra</a>, <a href="http://www.mackframework.com/">mack</a>, <a href="http://rubywaves.com/">waves</a>...</p>

<h2>The plot twist</h2>

<p>Now that Merb 1.0 is out, some people want to know what they should use for their next project. Merb or Rails? What's the difference, after all they seem to be doing the same thing. Someone starts a <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/ruby/comments/7d5u6/so_why_should_i_choose_merb_over_ruby_on_rails/">Reddit thread</a> asking this very same question to the community.... and the drama begins!</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>part 1:</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>Someone mentions that <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/ruby/comments/7d5u6/so_why_should_i_choose_merb_over_ruby_on_rails/c06ckgv">Merb has less code so it's easier to understand</a> the "underpinnings of your framework". <a href="http://bitsweat.net/">Jeremy Kemper aka Bitsweat</a> from Rails core team reply by saying that <a href="http://www.reddit.com/user/bitsweat/">Rails code base is only 1/4 bigger than Merb's</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>part 2:</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>Yehuda Katz, jumps to his shell, runs some commands and <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/ruby/comments/7d5u6/so_why_should_i_choose_merb_over_ruby_on_rails/c06d0f3">replies that Jeremy</a> did not count right and really, Merb is half the code size has Rails. He even writes a <a href="http://yehudakatz.com/2008/11/14/mythbusting-merb-style/">blog post to explain what he did</a> his main point being that Merb can run on subset of his code (merb-core) while Rails can't.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>part 3:</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>At this point, DHH already <a href="http://www.loudthinking.com/posts/29-the-rails-myths">started addressing</a> some of the reproaches the Merb community has brought on Rails. Interesting enough, DHH carefully never mentions Merb though. However just after wycats/Yehuda's post, DHH releases a post entitled: <a href="http://www.loudthinking.com/posts/33-myth-4-rails-is-a-monolith">Rails is a monolith</a>. In his post, DHH calls LOC comparison an "inverse dick measurement match". He goes even further and gives the size of some of Rails' components, mentions that there is a way in Rails to remove parts you don't want but that anyway "Why would you bother? And that's an answer I [DHH] don't quite have for you."</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>part 4 (I told you it was a real drama)</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>Yehuda considers that even though, DHH didn't mention him or Merb, "they" means the Merb community. Unfortunately, DHH doesn't allow comments on his site so Yehuda decides to write yet <a href="http://yehudakatz.com/2008/11/15/mythbusting-rails-is-not-a-monolith/">another blog post</a>. In his post, Yehuda deconstructs DHH arguments and tries to explain the philosphical difference between the two frameworks.</p>

<h2>Drama or no drama?</h2>

<p>There were a lot of comments on reddit and yehuda's blog, a lot of tweets were sent, Â but is there a real drama?</p>

<p>My answer is <strong>no</strong>.</p>

<p>The truth is that Merb was developed because some people like Ezra, Yehuda, myself and others were frustrated by some aspects of the Rails framework. We believed in the framework main concept but we were not sharing some of the core values or some of the details of the implementation.</p>

<p>We have nothing but respect for DHH and the Rails core team.<strong> To be honest, without Matz and without DHH, I wouldn't do the job I do today and my job would probably not be as much as what it is</strong>. Most, if not all of the Merb core team members contributed to Rails and are very familiar with its architecture. We just have a different philosophy/approach of problems.</p>

<p>There is also a lot of collaboration between the two teams. Ezra brought rack to Rails, Merb pushed rails to become thread-safe, during RubyConf, <a href="http://joshpeek.com/">Josh Peek</a> mentioned <a href="http://podcast.rubyonrails.org/programs/1/episodes/rubyconf-2008">porting run_later</a> (a Merb only feature) to Rails now that it's thread safe. On the other end, we based a lot of our framework on concepts proven by Rails.</p>

<p><strong>So what is it all about?</strong></p>

<p>It's just people arguing ideas. It's actually a very healthy thing for a community to do.</p>

<p>I'm not oviously talking about the Rails overall community. I do realize it might shake the Rails community a little bit, but I think it's for the best.</p>

<p>I also hope Sinatra, Waves, camping will join the debate. Sinatra for example is an awesome tiny framework. Merb has flat/very-flat structures which do something similar to Sinatra but with some differences. I think it's great we can talk freely about the philosophies behind each framework.</p>

<p>By putting arguments out there and arguing ideas without fighting, I strongly believe that each framework will just become better and it would be easier for developers to choose what framework fits their needs best.</p>

<p><strong>No drama then?</strong></p>

<p>Well, maybe a little bit, let me quote a quote from <a href="http://gettingreal.37signals.com/ch02_Have_an_Enemy.php">37signals book, getting real</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>Don't follow the leader</strong>
Marketers (and all human beings) are well trained to follow the leader. The natural instinct is to figure out what's working for the competition and then try to outdo it â€” to be cheaper than your competitor who competes on price, or faster than the competitor who competes on speed. The problem is that once a consumer has bought someone else's story and believes that lie, <strong>persuading the consumer to switch is the same as persuading him to admit he was wrong</strong>. And people hate admitting that they're wrong.</p></blockquote>

<p>â€”<a href="http://sethgodin.typepad.com/">Seth Godin</a>, author/entrepreneur (from <a href="http://www.moveahead1.com/articles/article_details.asp?id=33">Be a Better Liar</a>)</p>

<p>Godin makes a good point, some people feel threatened by a new solution competing with the one they currently use. Godin and 37 signals suggest that instead of competing on the same ground as the leader (in this case Rails), you should position yourself differently and that's what Merb has been doing since theÂ beginning.</p>

<p>That's probably why Yehuda reacted when Jeremy and David said that basically, Merb was no different than Rails.</p>

<p>Merb's point is not to be a faster Rails, instead Merb brings a different approach to the Ruby web development world. And that's the true identity of Merb.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>No need for trolling or making a big deal about what happened. Rails and Merb are both lead by opinionated/passionate people who have a different view on what their framework should do and how it should do it. Â Let's keep the dialogue open but let's not forget that all of us spend hours and hours offering software and the goal is to server the community no to fight.</p>

<p>Both Rails and Merb have pros and cons, learn more about the difference between the two frameworks, look at other solutions and more importantly evaluate your needs.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[merb 1.0 - tips part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2008/11/14/merb-10-tips-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2008-11-14T00:39:27+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2008/11/14/merb-10-tips-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Â </p>

<p>As you must know by now, last week,<a href="http://merbist.com/2008/11/09/merb-1-0-released"> Merb 1.0 got released</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://merbist.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/11/nsa_logo.gif"><img src="http://merbist.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/11/nsa_logo.gif" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Because we wanted to assure the release was fine, we asked <a href="http://engineyard.com">Engine Yard</a>, <a href="http://apple.com">Apple</a> and <a href="http://yellowpages.com">YellowPages.com</a> to help us by hiring the NSA to monitor Merb users. After all, we need to know what people complain about so we can fix it ASAP.</p>

<p>Turns out all the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ECHELON">echelon monitoring sites</a> were already busy. So we had to go back to good old IRC and <a href="http://search.twitter.com/search?q=merb">twitter search</a> ;)</p>

<p>The release looks pretty solid, thanks to all the people reported bugs during the release candidate cycle. Thanks guys!</p>

<p>However there are still few points of confusion I'd like to address.</p>

<h2>How do I require/request/load a plugin?</h2>

<p>I saw this question few times on IRC and someone after my <a href="http://orug.org">ORUG</a> merb presentation tonight asked me exactly the same thing. I promised <a href="http://peepcode.com/">Geoffrey Grosenbach</a> that I would update the RDoc but in the meantime here is quick explanation.</p>

<p>You should almost never use the require method to load a gem. Rubygems has a method called gem that takes a version as an argument:</p>

<p><code>require "rubygems"
gem "merb-core", "~&gt; 1.0"
</code></p>

<p>Using gem you can specify a version of the gem you want to load. Therefore you avoid loading an unexpected version of a gem. A few tricks to know (for regular Ruby code; keep reading for the Merb technique):</p>

<p>You can use "=1.0" to limit to version 1.0, or ">= 1.0" to load 1.0 and anything newer. My favorite trick is to use "~> 1.0" which means load latest version between 1.0 and 2.0</p>

<p>However when using Merb you don't want to load gems just whenever. Merb's bootup process starts by setting up the directory structure, and you typically want to load plugins after this point. To make this transparent to you, we have the #dependency method. The dependency method uses the gem method internally to load specific versions at the right time. Additionally, we may use it in the future to improve Merb's built-in bundling or dependency resolution. As a result, you should always use the dependency method, and not try to use require directly for Merb plugins.</p>

<p>It also comes with two tricks you should know about. Let's say you want to require a gem from github:</p>

<p><code>dependency "mattetti-awesomeâ€, "~&gt;1.0", :require_as =&gt; â€œawesomeâ€
</code></p>

<p>The example above is the same as:
<code>
gem "mattetti-awesome", "~1.0"
require "awesome"
</code>
Apart that it gets loaded when it's appropriate.</p>

<p>You can also pass a block after your dependency call:</p>

<p><code>dependency('jchris-couchrest', "&gt;= 0.5", :require_as =&gt; "couchrest") do
Â Â require "lib/custom_hack.rb"
endÂ </code></p>

<p>The block will be executed after the gem is loaded and required. Use a block if you want to perform some action after the dependency is loaded.</p>

<p>Finally the last trick lets you load a gem right when you declare the dependency:</p>

<p><code>dependency "nokogiriâ€, "~&gt;0.5", :immediate =&gt; true</code></p>

<h2>I have issues with merb -i and can't run the specs</h2>

<p>Few things here, first off, Merb forces you to use rubygems 1.3 because 1.2 is very buggy and the Rubygems maintainer suggested we do so. Rubygems let you define development-only dependencies, dependencies you don't need to have to run your library in production. These dependencies were designed to be used when developing a library, but in the case of Merb, they are used to define dependencies that you only need at development-time, but not in production.</p>

<p>In our case we defined webrat as a development dependency. That means you need Webrat to run your specs, but won't need it in production. Now here is something you should know, whenever you install a gem to develop it, you should use:</p>

<p><code>gem install "merb-core" --development
</code></p>

<p>The --development flag will install all the dev dependencies declared by the gem.  Now merb -i loads the code needed to make the request object available in the console, the problem is that this code also loads some test helpers which require webrat. We have a ticket open for that and will get to that soon.</p>

<p>In the mean time, make sure you have webrat and nokogiri installed. (Nokogiri requires you have a somehow recent version of libxml2, which comes with OSX, but not all Linux distributions).</p>

<p>People reported some issues updating rubygems, Robby Colvin wrote a <a href="http://robbycolvin.com/archives/merbrubygems-upgrade-errors/">nice article</a> explaining how to get pass this issue.</p>

<h2>Issues with action-args not loading</h2>

<p>Some people reported issues with loading action-args. Turns out it's some sort of weird issue with hoe (the library) and a some of action-args deps. If that happens to you, update hoe:<code>
</code></p>

<p><code>$ sudo gem install hoe
</code></p>

<h2>I generated an app and it doesn't work with JRuby</h2>

<p>If you generate a merb using merb-gen app my-app-name it generates a merb stack app. It's an opinionated bundle with everything you might need including jQuery, DataMapper and a bunch of plugins. The problem is that DataMapper doesn't run on JRuby yet so it won't work.</p>

<p>Instead you should generate a core application:</p>

<p><code>merb-gen core app-name</code></p>

<p>This way you create a blank app with no dependencies. Then add what you need. <a href="http://wiki.merbivore.com/faqs/merb_components">Here is a list of dependencies</a> for a merb stack app and what they do.</p>

<h2>Thanks</h2>

<p>Finally I would like to thank the Ruby community from Japan. First because many people came to RubyConf all the way from Japan. I'm personally sorry I couldn't meet you all. Thankfully some people started a new chat channel on lingr: <a href="http://www.lingr.com/room/merb.jp">merb.jp</a> and I could meet more Japanese Merbists. Because the Merb team thinks is important that Merb is being used outside of the English speaking world and because we need feedback from other countries, I decided to make the trip to RubyKaigi 2009. Hopefully we will be able to have some talks about Merb :)Â  I would also want to thank Erubis author, Makoto Kuwata for translating the<a href="http://merbist.com/2008/11/09/merb-1-0-released"> Merb 1.0 annoucement post</a> in Japanese.</p>

<h2>Finally</h2>

<p>Here are the slides from my talk at <a href="http://orug.org">Orug</a>, a quick presentation of Merb. I'll be at <a href="http://qconsf.com/sf2008/conference/">QCon</a> next week to talk about <a href="http://qconsf.com/sf2008/tracks/show_track.jsp?trackOID=172">Ruby for the Enterprise</a>. Thanks <a href="http://railsenvy.com/">Gregg</a> for thinking of me!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/mattetti/merb-presentation-at-orug-presentation?type=powerpoint">Merb presentation at ORUG</a>Â </p>

<p>View SlideShare <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/mattetti/merb-presentation-at-orug-presentation?type=powerpoint">presentation</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Merb 1.0 released]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2008/11/09/merb-1-0-released/"/>
    <updated>2008-11-09T22:47:25+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2008/11/09/merb-1-0-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://flickr.com/photos/absolutely_loverly/120000855/"><img src="http://farm1.static.flickr.com/47/120000855_c7d39781f7_m.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://d.hatena.ne.jp/kwatch/20081112/1226448192"><img src="http://merbist.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/11/nihon-japan-48.png" alt="" /></a>
<a href="http://d.hatena.ne.jp/kwatch/20081112/1226448192">Japanese translation</a></p>

<p>On November 7, <a href="http://yehudakatz.com/">Yehuda Katz</a> gave a talk at <a href="http://rubyconf.org">RubyConf</a> and made 3 major announcements:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://engineyard.com">Engine Yard</a> to offer <a href="http://engineyard.com/merbsupport">Merb support</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://ma-agile.com/">m|a agile</a> to offer <a href="http://ma-agile.com/training/">professional training</a></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Merb 1.0 released!</strong></p></li>
</ul>


<p>The first announcement is pretty substantial. <a href="http://engineyard.com">Engine Yard</a> has been financially supporting <a href="http://merbivore.com">Merb</a> by letting some of their staff work on Merb, fly them to different conferences and sponsoring events like <a href="http://merbcamp.com">Merb Camp</a>. Engine Yard didn't yet announce the price structure but <strong>having the option for enterprise level support for Merb is just awesome</strong>.</p>

<p><a href="http://railstips.org">John Nunemaker</a> made an interesting comment during RubyConf <a href="http://pivotallabs.com/">Pivotal</a> Party. Something special about Merb is that it was designed to fit the needs of an audience instead of trying to create a series of tools to build a specific type of website. Having Engine Yard help to finance Merb dev and offer support is very reassuring. It's something already done by many other OSS projects such as Ubuntu, MySQL etc...</p>

<p><a href="http://ma-agile.com/training"><img src="http://merbist.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/11/merb-training-small-238x300.gif" alt="" /></a>The second announcement Yehuda made was about <a href="http://ma-agile.com/training/">Merb Training</a>. I'm probably pretty biased since I am at the origin of this project. I know for a fact that a lot of people were waiting for 1.0 to get started with Merb. We are also working on getting more documentation out, and 3 books are coming up. Still, the best way to learn is to sit down with people who know Merb who can teach you the way its intended to be used.</p>

<p>Training will allow you to benefit a lot from being with other people who also share the same desire to <strong>master Ruby's most powerful and flexible web framework</strong>.</p>

<p>What's also really exciting is that <a href="http://yehudakatz.com">Yehuda Katz</a>, Merb's lead developer, agreed to be a tutor for the course. I can't imagine a better way to learn. Check <a href="http://ma-agile.com/training/">this page</a> for more information about the next training session or get in contact with me if you want to organize a training session for your company.</p>

<h3>Finally, the <strong>big news was the announcement of Merb 1.0</strong>!</h3>

<p>Merb 1.0 went through 5 release candidates and was finally marked as final. In the last few months, the Merb team worked hard to make things easier for people who want to get started in no time.</p>

<p>Let's quickly look at why Merb is awesome:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Merb is Modular</strong>. Merb is not a monolithic framework. You can pick and choose what you need. Create a 1 file app "Ã  la Sinatra" or a rich web app "Ã  la Rails". Merb has many components. Only requires the ones you need and save precious resources. (Merb doesn't believe in 1 size fits all)</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Merb is agnostic</strong> (kinda). Because people have different needs and different believes, Merb won't force you to use one ORM or another. Same thing goes for the template engine or for the JavaScript library you want to use. ActiveRecord, DataMapper, Sequel, RelaxDb, Haml, Erb, Prototype, jQuery... choose which one you want and change whenever you want.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Merb <em>can</em> be opinionated</strong>. Merb offers a default stack using DataMapper and jQuery, authentication, exceptions and caching setup for you. However, creating your own stack is dead easy. As a matter of fact, the guys at <a href="http://yellowpages.com">yellowpages.com</a> are using Merb and were talking about creating their own stack using Sequel.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Merb let you reuse your code</strong>. Borrowed from <a href="http://www.djangoproject.com/">Django</a>, Merb has something called "slices". Slices are mini apps you can run standalone or mounted within another app. A slice is a great way to write code you can reuse. Unlike plugins which extend the framework features, slices are a way to provide encapsulated content. (<a href="http://blog.davidchelimsky.net/">David Chelimsky,</a> RSpec's author and maintainer actually said that slices where his favorite feature in Merb 1.0)</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Merb has an API</strong>. You might be wondering why having an API is awesome. Well, the truth is that the Merb Team spent time marking methods public, which are guaranteed to not break until the next major release (any change to the public API will be well documented). There is also a plugin API meaning that plugin developers won't have to worry about upgrades if they stick to the plugin API.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Merb is fast.</strong> Even though Ruby the language isn't really fast and contrary to popular opinion, Ruby for the web is one of the fastest solutions out there. (Even Rails is <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/wycats/merb-camp-keynote-presentation">way faster than all the mainstream PHP frameworks</a>) And that's what Merb is proving by being one of the fastest web framework available on the market. <a href="http://railsenvy.com/">Jason Seifer</a> will be interested to know that Merb isn't scared to scale ;) As a matter of fact, Merb is going to scale even better in the next few months as we are planning to integrate <a href="http://swiftiply.swiftcore.org/index.html">Swiftiply</a> and do some totally awesome stuff to spawn/reap workers based load. (more about that in few weeks).</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Matz likes Merb</strong>. Ruby's daddy, Yukihiro Matsumoto told us he likes the flexibility of Merb and the fact that the framework doesn't create a DSL on top of Ruby. He even told us that he's going to introduce his company to Merb! We were obviously very honored and for us, it validates months of work by dozens of contributors. Here is a transcript of Matz comments about Merb and the Ruby web world:</p></li>
</ul>


<p>[caption id="attachment_213" align="alignleft" width="125" caption="Yukihiro Matsumoto aka Matz"]<a href="http://ruby-lang.org"><img src="http://merbist.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/11/yukihiro_matsumoto_125px.jpg" alt="Yukihiro Matsumoto aka Matz" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<blockquote><p>"Everyone outside of the Ruby community understands that we only have 1 web application framework, named Rails, but it's not true in any sense. We have several post-Rails frameworks, which is very good, and I believe in diversity.</p></blockquote>

<p>Merb has a bright future for the people who are not satisfied by the fixed ways in Rails.Â  I think that Merb will give users more freedom in a Ruby-ish way of programming.</p>

<p>I'm not really a web-guy, so i don't judge any of them [frameworks], but Rails does some kind of drastic change on the language itself like in Active Support.Â  But Ruby has its own culture and technological atmosphere in the language so that keeping that makes me feel easier."</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Merb is memory friendly and therefore cheap</strong>. Merb is Open Source and free, but hosting an application costs money. Merb memory footprint is tiny compared to other solutions and that means that hosting will cost you less. (interesting when you think that EngineYard help developing Merb :p) Using <a href="http://www.rubyenterpriseedition.com/">Ruby Entreprise Edition</a>, you will even use less memory, meaning you save even more money ;) By the way, Matz told me this morning that the Ruby core team is working on their own solution for a better GC and it should be available soon. (Ruby 1.9.x)</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Merb source code is easy to read</strong>. Because <a href="http://github.com/wycats/merb/tree/master">Merb code</a> is modular and because Merb has a concept of an API, reading Merb's source code is pretty easy. On top of that, Merb itself uses RSpec making tests really easy to read and understand.Â  What's great when the source code is easy to read is that developers can quickly check the source code if they want to understand how things work. We also get better patches from contributors and we keep our code clean. We believe in the theory of the "Broken Windows" by James Q. Wilson and George L. Kelling:</p></li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p>"Consider a building with a few broken windows. If the windows are not repaired, the tendency is for vandals to break a few more windows. Eventually, they may even break into the building, and if it's unoccupied, perhaps become squatters or light fires inside.</p></blockquote>

<p>Or consider a sidewalk. Some litter accumulates. Soon, more litter accumulates. Eventually, people even start leaving bags of trash from take-out restaurants there or breaking into cars."</p>

<p>I guess I could keep on going with other reasons why Merb is so awesome, but let's keep some for another post ;)</p>

<p>In conclusion, on behalf of the Merb core team, I'd like to thank all the Merb contributors, Ezra Zygmuntowic (creator of Merb), Yehuda Katz (Merb lead developer), Matz (Ruby creator) and finally DHH &amp; the Rails core team. One more thing:</p>

<p><code>
$ sudo gem install merb
$ merb-gen app my-awesome-merb-app
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Merb 1.0 RC5]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2008/11/03/merb-10-rc5/"/>
    <updated>2008-11-03T18:50:21+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2008/11/03/merb-10-rc5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As you might have noticed, we've been pushing a lot of Release Candidates out the door. The reason is that we want to make sure 1.0 is really ready for showtime!</p>

<p>We are also getting a lot of bug reports that help us focusing on the main issues. Today RC5 was pushed to a RubyForge mirror close to you and <a href="http://yehudakatz.com/2008/11/03/merb-rc5-final-rc/">here is a report from Yehuda Katz</a>, <a href="http://merbivore.com">Merb</a> lead developer.</p>

<p>This is the final RC before we ship 1.0 final at <a href="http://rubyconf.org/">RubyConf</a>. Here is a really quick rundown of the bugfixes and improvement added to this release:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://github.com/brynary/webrat/tree/master">Webrat</a> integration out of the box. (<a href="http://github.com/wycats/merb/tree/master/merb-core/spec/public/webrat/webrat_spec.rb">see example</a>)</p></li>
<li><p>Improved Merb bundling</p></li>
<li><p>spec view helpers now use <a href="http://tenderlovemaking.com/2008/10/30/nokogiri-is-released/">nokogiri</a> (with rexml as fallback )</p></li>
<li><p>new <a href="http://github.com/wycats/merb/tree/master/merb-core/spec/public/test/view_matchers_spec.rb#L16-36">have_selector</a> spec helper using CSS3 compatible selector.</p></li>
<li><p>The entire Merb spec suite now runs correctly on JRuby &amp; Windows.</p></li>
<li><p>Once again improved jRuby support.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>In other news, we setup a nightly gem server so people who want to be on Edge don't have to deal with git and we call also test gem releases before pushing to RubyForge. More about that coming up during RubyConf.</p>

<p>Talking about <a href="http://rubyconf.org/">RubyConf</a>,Â  <a href="http://yehudakatz.com">Yehuda</a> and <a href="http://merbist.com/about/">I</a> will be in Orlando enjoying a good Ruby meetup. Come and chat with us if you are interested in starting using Merb, or if you have been using Merb. Also, please come and see us if you hate Merb and care tell us why. We're looking forward to meet you all.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Merb Pre Sprint Meeting]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2008/10/07/merb-pre-sprint-meeting/"/>
    <updated>2008-10-07T22:53:53+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2008/10/07/merb-pre-sprint-meeting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3171/2424765496_43008cbd29.jpg?v=0" alt="" />Some of Los SeÃ±ores del Merb, AKA the Merb "core team" met tonight in a secret location in San Diego, CA. Obviously, we had to meet in a Mexican restaurant and enjoy <a href="http://www.rubios.com/">Tuesday Fish Taco night special</a> ;)</p>

<p>While not everybody could make the trip, Yehuda, Andy, Daniel, Carl and myself met to plan the very first Merb Sprint.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, Michael and Fabien could not make it, but will work remotely during the next few days.</p>

<p>Yehuda sent attendees the following explanations about the Scrum:</p>

<blockquote><p>"Tomorrow morning, the Merb core team will be setting up around 9am in the sprint room, setting up the git infrastructure for the event, and setting up CI and a wiki for the sprint.</p></blockquote>

<p>We're going to be breaking up into a few teams: an inline documentation team, a getting-up-and-running team, and merb-stack team. Each team will be led by a core team member, who will be responsible for pushing the work of the team up to the main merb repository, which will be manned by me throughout the sprint."</p>

<p>The sprint will focus on 4 main points:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>inline documentation</p></li>
<li><p>getting-up-and-running</p></li>
<li><p>Merb-stack</p></li>
<li><p>reported tickets (lead remotely by Michael)</p></li>
</ul>


<p>This is a really exciting time and things are looking good.</p>

<p>For those wondering about Merb-Stack... well just wait few days and you'll see ;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Merb Edge update (Oct 6th 2008)]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2008/10/06/merb-edge-update-oct-6th-2008/"/>
    <updated>2008-10-06T20:50:15+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2008/10/06/merb-edge-update-oct-6th-2008</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><p>Mode changes to init.rb, user updating to a newer version or Merb will need to add</p>

<p>c[:log_file] = Merb.root / "log" / "development.log"</p></li>
</ul>


<p>to their init.rb file or config/environments/development.rb for instance. (Newly generated apps are already setup properly)</p>

<ul>
<li><p>We made some changes to the way Rake files work. Merb-core doesn't require the rspec tasks anymore so Test::Unit see annoying rspec tasks. Once again people upgrading to the latest version of Merb need to make a small change and add:</p>

<p>require 'spec/rake/spectask'</p></li>
</ul>


<p>to their rake file. Newly generated applications using RSpec already have that line setup.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>In the last few days, <a href="http://yehudakatz.com/">Yehuda</a> merged in his branch with the new "request-testing feature". This is a new way of testing your apps. It makes testing a real request going through a controller and being rendered in a view, something quite easy, Merb interegration tests here we go!. <a href="http://gist.github.com/14910">Check here</a> to see a example of what you can now do. Rails + Rspec users might be surprised by this choice, and I've scheduled to interview Yehuda so he can explain why and when you want to use this way of testing your app. (Don't miss his talk at <a href="http://merbcamp.com">MerbCamp</a> next week)</p></li>
<li><p>Talking about full stack testing, Merb is almost entirely full stack tested. What does that mean? Take a look at <a href="http://github.com/wycats/merb-more/tree/master/merb-helpers">merb-helpers</a> specs in <a href="http://github.com/wycats/merb-more">merb-more</a>. Form builders are tested through a real app available from spec/fixture/app, the views are rendered in the specs and the results are check to make sure they will work for you in your real application. Avoiding using too many mocks and stubs helped us really test things in the contet of a real app and avoid a great amount of ghost bugs. Specs might run a bit slower but we believe Merb now has better testing suite than before. More coming up about this topic.</p></li>
<li><p>Ohh and we released Merb 0.9.8 "Time Machine", last release before 1.0RC1 ;)</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[problems with urls in Merb HEAD?]]></title>
    <link href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2008/09/30/problems-with-urls-in-merb-head/"/>
    <updated>2008-09-30T22:24:29+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2008/09/30/problems-with-urls-in-merb-head</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I actually run into a small problem when updated an older Merb app. Here was how my router looked like:</p>

<pre><code>Merb::Router.prepare do |r|
  r.resources :channels do |channels|
    channels.resources :shows do |shows|
      shows.resources :episodes
    end
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>But after updating to the latest version of Merb, I got links looking like:</p>

<pre><code>http://localhost:4000/channels/#&lt;Channel:0x27b7300&gt;/shows
</code></pre>

<p>The first thing to do is to read <a href="http://github.com/carllerche/merb-core-enterprise-edition/wikis/whats-new-with-the-router">Carl's wiki about the latest Router changes</a>.</p>

<p>Carl explains that things got cleaned up in the router code and my routes should now look like:</p>

<pre><code>Merb::Router.prepare do |r|
  r.resources :channels do
    resources :shows do |shows|
      resources :episodes
    end
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>However that won't be enough..  You see my url used to look like that:</p>

<pre><code>url(:channel_shows, :channel_id =&gt; channel)
</code></pre>

<p>Now I can simplify it to:</p>

<pre><code>url(:channel_shows, channel)
</code></pre>

<p>That still won't fix the problem, since the real problem comes from the fact that I was on Merb HEAD but not DataMapper HEAD. Updating DM clears things up. That's the price to pay to be on HEAD ;)</p>

<p>FYI the problem comes from the fact that DM doesn't add a to_params method to its objects. Rails users might recognize that method used to convert an object into a string to create a route, something not really ORM agnostic and frowned upon by the DM/Merb teams.</p>

<p>Merb lets you specify the param to use for your routes using the identify method. Read <a href="http://github.com/carllerche/merb-core-enterprise-edition/wikis/whats-new-with-the-router">Carl's wiki page </a>for more cool stuff and see how to create some cool stuff like url slugs etc..</p>

<p>Note that even if you are using ActiveRecord, you'll need to update merb_activerecord as the new identify rules were updated in the ORM plugins.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
